not to fall, and he will be the light of the nations, and the hope of those whose hearts
are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits, 1st Denoc, chapter 48, verses 4 through 5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge, but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
hour time many year into break free of the prison of a flat secular
to see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation,
the union of the scene and unseen as made by God
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord.
spirits. Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers, hunters of the Hobgoblin
Hords. You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast. My co-host, Father Stephen D'Young,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana. And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Daymak, and I'm not in a
maize. That's right. I am in Chesterton, Dune Land, Indiana, itself, aka the poor man's Ohio,
So, ancient faith ministries headquarters, and I am actually in the same room as a
very own Matroska Trudy the tank Richter. So if you hear her giggling in the background,
that is the tank herself. We discovered it the last few days, her secret nickname that she had
when she was but a calo youth. And we're live. And if you're listening to us live, you can call us
855-237-2346, and you could talk to us. And we're going to get your calls in second half of the show.
But I said, what?
you that I am going to be the one answering your call. So if you call, you're not going to hear
the Melodia's voice of Matroska Trudy the Tank Richter, instead you're going to just go straight
to hold and we're just going to have sheer anarchy. So you better behave here on our 100th episode
of Lord of Spirit's podcast. Having descended to the heart of the Milstrom and the belly of the beast,
you are now drunk with power. That's right. I can do anything. First, they were going to put me out on
on kind of the factory floor.
here at AFM HQ, but I'm like, why does Trudy get to be in the soundproof room taking the phone calls?
And I have to be like in front of some green screen or whatever the heck it is.
Oh Trudy just walked out. I don't know what's going on. I could just start pressing buttons.
This would be really fun. She probably does that normally during the show,
which is don't even have buttons or walk out. Maybe some of both.
Yeah, so. All right. Well, this 100th episode is sponsored by the Orthodox Studies Institute at
it's saint constancy
College which exists to advance the study and application of Orthodox Christianity and
faithfulness to holy tradition.
OSI is currently offering a live online course on the book of Enoch taught by you, Father
Stephen Dianne.
The course is underway, but by popular demand, OSI has reopened registration.
You can catch up on the recordings of earlier classes and participate in live classes going
forward.
Live class at this point.
Oh, there you go.
To learn more.
go to Orthodox Studies.org.
LOS, registration is now open for OSI's second course,
which is Holy Women of Byzantium,
which begins in October.
You can go to orthodoxstudies.org slash LOS
to learn more.
This is indeed our 100th episode.
I was gonna say 100th anniversary episode.
That's right, kids.
We've been doing this since 1990.
I know it feels like it had a tyranny,
but that's because you're doing it with me.
It kind of does.
But it is our fourth anniversary episode.
So, over 99 episodes, I'm Patone now when we just started talking.
We have drone-down four, and I checked this.
I edited it all up by listening to it once again with a stopwatch.
270 hours, 57 minutes, 21 seconds.
That makes the average LOS episode about two hours and 45 minutes long.
Probably would have been longer, but a lot of our earlier ones were...
Yeah, because this was supposed to be a one hour show.
I don't even remember that!
We're like, you have to be like 45 minutes to an hour.
Ha ha ha.
Fooled y'all.
So, yes, so this is our 100th anniversary episode.
We're in a celebratory mood.
As far as Stephen said, I do feel drunk with power here
being an AFM HQ.
But we are going to actually talk about real stuff.
The word unchanging is a word that's often
used to describe Orthodox Christianity.
The sonata kind of orthodoxy even says that
Orthodox Christianity is the faith which is established the universe, a bold statement.
Yet, if you look at the evidence for Christian worship many centuries ago, it is not exactly
the same as Orthodox worship here in the 21st century.
And clearly it's very different from what we see in Genesis chapter 1.
So what does unchanging actually mean?
And is there acceptable change?
And is this the episode?
Well...
we finally completely succumb to the panheresy of ecumenism.
Well, I think you already did.
That's what people say.
On one of your other programs.
But I will not.
Oh, well, thank you.
Thank you.
It's not because I am some stalwart
of the Orthodox faith.
It's just I'm petty and I just more different than me.
Yeah.
Yeah
So I'm going to go on too far from you having descended there and now being just rife with universal power.
That connects to a grievance that I didn't get to air before we started, so now I'm going to air it.
Oh! Let it out!
Which is not in any way related to the program.
So, you know, or our topic tonight.
I know you're shocked, but I'm not talking about something unrelated.
But it is weighty on my mind.
So I
f
Finally got to play the Mortal Kombat one DLC that came out Tuesday.
Oh.
And the whole premise of this thing, the whole premise of it.
Now look, it's Mortal Kombat, right?
So like story mode, I'm not expecting Shakespeare, right?
I'm expecting different color ninjas kicking each other.
That's basically what I'm expecting.
I'm expecting a very thin plot linking together a series of martial arts battles.
Right.
Okay
If your premise is going to be that Titan Lord Havoc has gotten mad with power in another timeline,
and is trying to bring chaos and anarchy, as he says over and over and over again,
chaos and anarchy to all the timelines.
And you could tell he wants chaos and anarchy because all his minions have mohawks.
Um, right.
If this is your whole setup, and this is what you're doing through the whole story, then
when I get to the final confrontation with him, right?
To try to stop him from bringing chaos and anarchy
to every universe.
He can't say,
buy you've disrupted my plans.
Okay.
Right?
Because if the highest value is chaos and anarchy,
why would there be a plan for one?
The correct response for a B would be,
you're welcome.
Because you would want that.
Right.
Because that's the goal.
It's chaos and anarchy.
the dream.
But he wants to be his cast and Eric.
This whole thing.
Right, this whole thing has driven me nuts for a long time.
Back in the day I had World of Warcraft, there was a guild on our server called Order of
Anarchy.
And it was just like what?
Wow.
Yes.
Just words.
Yeah.
Okay.
So, grievance aired.
I'm sure you've been heard.
Yes.
Come on, NetherRealm Studios.
You could do better.
You only have to do...
slightly better. We set the bar low on these things. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So what we're actually
talking about is not related to the Lin Kueh or any other magic-wielding ninja forces
slash cybernetic conspiracy. Indeed. But we're kind of in a way picking up on what we talked
about last time.
where last time we went way back into the long ago time,
even before the distant year 2000,
even before 2000 BC, back to the Stone Age.
And we really were talking about the continuity
last time.
The continuity of the worship of the true God,
Right in all.
in all generations. And so tonight, now, we're going to be talking about the fact that,
okay, yes, you talked about that continuity, right? But within that, we also made the point
of various distinctions, right, between, for example, different religious forms, like
between paganism and Judaism and Christianity. So there's not just continuity, there's also
discontinuity.
And this begs the question, how much change or variation does it take within continuity
to make a discontinuity?
Yeah, because we're not saying that all religions are the same man.
Right.
I'm like certain very high ranking religious leaders I understood said that they're kind
of all a path to God in one way or another.
Yeah.
That guy's always saying wacky stuff.
Right, like God bless him.
Yeah, it's gonna be, doesn't have a Twitter account.
Actually, I think he does.
He has like nine Twitter accounts in multiple languages.
Does he post on the map?
I mean, I'm pretty sure it's somebody who works for him.
Yeah, I wonder if there's like a Twitter legate.
Ooh, anyway.
So, so right, so we clearly weren't trying to make
this perennialist point even while we were
stressing the idea
of continuity. So now we're going to talk about where the discontinuity comes in and where
that break is. So last time, just to sort of recap a little because every episode is someone's
first. Yeah, I just feel bad for the people for whom this is their first. If this is your
first episode, go ahead and call in. We'd like to hear from you. And just be with like,
like to walk with you in your confusion.
don't ask for a recap of the last 99 episodes.
What do you call it?
Because we can't do that.
Best I can do is a paperback book.
Yeah, yeah, or two or three or six.
Yeah, yeah.
So last time, right?
And we're gonna, this is our want.
We went backwards last time.
Right, we sort of worked our way back to the Stone Age.
So we'll recap it forwards.
That's nice.
So
Not only will this be a refresher, but if anyone is confused by the last episode
Maybe this will help. Yeah
So we started out talking about the very early talking about humans in
Hunter Gather societies
having maintained sort of a conception of the one God
Who created everything? Yep, although even within that
you start to see some drift.
in that one God starts to become a Sky God.
And once you start getting a Sky God,
then you're on your way.
It's a Sky Daddy.
Yeah, exactly.
Flang's spaghetti monster.
They had spaghetti the hunter gathered.
They found it in the wild.
The wet bread.
Flang wet bread monster.
The, the, the, that, you're well on your way
to having gods of other things.
Once you have a godly
that you associate is particularly a sky god.
So there's already drift happening,
but we don't have what would later come
to be called paganism yet.
Right.
And we talked about how paganism as such,
the kind of paganism that we find
being pretty ubiquitous in the ancient world,
you find beginning and growing out
of the Neolithic revolution
as people move from hunter
to agrarian, they start to masticating plants and animals. They start living in one place, growing food.
This is where you begin to see first, you see the sort of sky, father, earth mother, kind of
paradigm emerge, and then as life in settlement starts, you start seeing gods of this, that, and the other.
Then you start to see
Sacrifices happening in distinct sacred places, right rather than people stopping and building altars as they travel. Yeah, there's like
trines
Right temples tabernacles while not take pilgrimages to and then become the sites of settlements
permanence
settlements
You have still within it you have the phenomenon of nomadism
Buddhism and people.
who are living nomatically still, when you look at their religion, it's still closer to
those earlier roots, which of course we as Christians believe is at least closer to the truth
and we talked about how there's also a thread going through here of people who are worshiping the
true God. We see that spelled out not just in terms of from Moses on but even in Genesis
this and not just Abraham Abraham.
Kisadak, who is someone living in a pagan society, but who is still worshiping the Trugat.
Which how does that work?
But it just does.
That's only God's service.
The remnant.
Yeah, exactly.
And so then we talked about the shifts in the mid-first millennium BC that's referred
to as the axial age, the sort of shifts that happen really across the world.
shifts that happen both within paganism from sort of the day
reguru paganism of the day to paganisms that are in various
ways more refined.
Yeah, I think like the way that I kind of works out of my
head is it's sort of intellectualizing on some level.
You know, you start getting doctrines and texts and this kind
of thing to express.
As you said, more refined to express a more kind of...
verbal, I think, form of religion.
Right.
If there is that move to a focus on texts, a more intense focus on texts arise in literacy
rates and that does reshape religious practice.
We didn't get into this last time because it wasn't strictly on topic, but something's
very similar happens in terms of the shift of religion.
within Europe when the reformation happens and you have the printing press.
And you have another huge rise in literacy rates.
That you again have
religion becoming more text focused and more intellectualized as a result.
Right so that's
something that happens. But that happened not only within paganism but as we
talked about that happened within Judy.
and that's part of what produces what we call second-table Judaism with the
synagogue system with a renewed focus on the tax particularly of the Torah, but
then of the other Hebrew scriptures, and then ultimately is continued into
Christianity. Right, and so we talked about sort of those shifts, but that within
those shifts there is this overarching.
continuity. So to start out tonight we want to focus in a little bit on those shifts happening within
Judaism. The way we see what we were talking about last time, last time we were talking
mainly about the pagan world and with broad strokes. Now we're going to focus in on how we see
this reflected, especially in the scriptures but also within Israelite religion, Judaism and Christianity.
Okay, so buckle up everybody. We're doing another massive sweep of thousands. I thought about
this a little bit earlier today because I went into Chicago and I went to what is now called
the Institute for the Study of Ancient Cultures, but until a year and a half ago was called
the Oriental Institute. And I mean, I was looking at artifacts that were literally like six
to 8,000 years old in some cases, or 4 to 6.
I don't know, but I mean, it was,
I could hear Carl Sagan in my head saying billions
and billions.
What's that at all?
It's not that old.
But that's sort of level of historical scale
that you just can't, you just really can't imagine.
Yeah, and yet they're human artifacts.
They're human artifacts.
It was crazy.
Yeah, crazy.
It was, yeah, it was,
Not millions.
Wild to see, like the newest stuff in there was from,
I don't know, like AD 800 or something,
like that, but the vast majority of it. And I have to say to everybody, by the way, since
I'm mentioning this place, if you're in Chicago, you should check out this museum, because
it's basically a Lord of Spirits museum. I mean, it kind of is. Have you ever been to
it, Father? I have not been there. Oh, you should totally, I mean, and it's not big either.
Like you can, you can look at all that a fairly leisurely pace within the space of just
a couple hours. But a lot of the cultures that we talk about on the show are represented
that museum.
If you're in Chicago, people go have a look.
And actually having listened to this show,
you will find it to be a rather rich experience
versus just walking in there cold without any talk
of things like a Lamassu, which they have one.
I did send you a photo of me standing in front of that thing.
Yeah, standing in front of you.
Yeah.
Fortunately, you weren't posed in a goofy way.
And no, I don't.
Yeah.
I mean, I was standing literally in the front of an image
someone else is a little...
lesser gods, so yeah, no goofy poses.
Also, if you're in Chicago, you should go and get muffins
from Mindy's bakery.
Oh, dooly noted.
Just as it is, side.
Muffins from Mindy's.
Yeah, so yeah, so these shifts, as we said,
are not just pressing out there in the pagan world,
but they're present within Judaism and Christianity.
And yet, right, and this is why we're focusing here,
we're gonna say there's a continuity, right?
A very real and strict continuity from-
That's right, daring.
From Genesis through Revelation and into Christianity.
Yeah.
Right.
We're not gonna say these are different religions.
There are shifts that happen. These shifts we've been talking about are reflected in there.
And so that's why we're now sort of refocusing on this. When we're talking about what is the latitude?
How do shifts happen? Is every shift to change? Is every change a break?
I feel like these are song lyrics are quoting but I'm pretty sure they're not.
But, like, wait, I'm never sure when you're quoting lyrics.
So, because you just, I mean, you-
speak politically very naturally. That's what you were also digging the crates. It's two references.
So people for centuries will puzzle over what I've created here. So the first sort of these shifts
that we see reflected in scriptures in Genesis chapter 4 verse 26. So we're not starting in
Genesis 1, 1 this time.
Close, a couple pages.
And that's in one of, that's in the genealogy of Seth.
One of the genealogies there in Genesis 4.
Every genealogies are everybody's favorite thing in the Bible.
But there's this comment about Seth's son Inosh.
Right, so this is as presented in the genealogy Adam's grandson.
Yeah.
It says son inosh, not inak inosh, and inak comes later.
And it says that in his day people began to call upon the name of Yahweh.
Yeah, which on its face seems kind of weird like wait a minute.
Wasn't Adam talking to him? What Seth talking was an able talking to him?
Yes. Yeah.
So
but this is reflecting a shift and calling upon the name of Yahweh or as it's usually in English Bible's calling upon the name of the Lord.
the Lord yeah but it's always refers to worship.
Right. This is over and over again in Genesis to the patriarchal narratives. He built an altar
and there he called upon the name of the Lord. That doesn't mean he was just yelling the Lord's name
over and over again. He was worshipping there. So we could translate this meaningfully
that this is when people started to worry about it.
worship Yahweh, which again is why their Andrew said, they weren't doing that before.
Right. We know that able at the very least, we know that able at the very least was doing it.
Offer, sacrifice. That's right. Yeah. Right. So it seems strange that it says, and then
they began to call upon the name of Yahweh. Right. What is it that began exactly? So what
What this is talking about is a shift that happens as humanity is multiplying on the earth.
Right. And once you have humanity multiplying and spreading out, right, then you have the
beginning of religion. Before this, to throw some of our friends a bone, it was a relationship
of religion. But just had a bunch of even, even jocals who loved us until this moment.
for
On, it's a religion. It's not a relationship.
Because it's number one, it's not direct. And number two, right, we're not talking about just
there's one big family on earth. And the head of that family is leading it in the worship of God.
We're talking about lots of families. They're spreading out. Right. Therefore, you have individual
heads of families offering sacrifices in different places. But you also have,
When you go
over to the genealogy of Cain. We've talked about that a fair amount. We're going to
obliquely hear touch on giants so get obliquely excited. There are other names being called
upon. Yep. There are other things starting to be worshiped in the city that Cain built.
Over there in Cainland. And so there is now we could now talk about religion, meaning
Let's get to the generation.
of Enoch. That's what this is saying. There are people who are worshiping Gowai the
true God. There are other people out there worshiping other things in different places.
Right. And so we see this pattern that we referred to last time of sort of earlier pre-settled
religion being
Preserving an earlier stage of religion.
Right.
So Abram is living in an idolatrous city.
But they've got temples and all that going on.
Right.
You've got paganism run and wild.
We're well-post-deolithic revolution here by millennia.
notice the situation with Abram. God
comes that appears to Abraham in person.
Yeah, which presumably, I mean,
we don't get any records, I should say,
of that happening.
Like there are times when it says
that God speaks to Noah, right?
But is it this in person sense?
I don't know.
That he sees him face to face.
No.
No, that's Abraham and then Moses.
Yeah.
Um, but uh, so...
He's called this idolatrous city and is called to leave that city and return to living
essentially as a nomad, not only as he spends years traversing the known world and the fertile
crescent to get to Canaan, but even once he's in Canaan, he's not, he doesn't go and move
to a city a lot does and that goes badly.
Abraham doesn't move into a city. Abraham continues to live nomatically on the
and move from place to place.
And as we've said before,
like this is one of the themes that runs through,
especially the Old Testament,
is this idea that the, you know,
putting down roots and building cities
is less than ideal,
is not the paratosanical life
that was given to Adam and Eve.
Right. It may not be bad in it of itself,
but it's dangerous.
Yeah. Yeah.
Most cities have no problems.
Yeah, yeah, you know there's big city women try and vamp you
That isn't obscure reference
In fact if you get that reference and you can tell me who said it on television
Call in
Don't call in with guesses. I'm looking over at the I'm actually looking at the phone right now to see if it's lighting up
You have to know and you can't go go go people you can't go you have to know who said that and where
so
And so we see this pattern
then in Genesis that the places
where the worship of the true God is preserved
is among the Abrahamites.
Like the Midianites, like Jethro,
Moses' father-in-law has preserved the worship of the true God.
And some of the edomites have.
But not all of the Abrahamites even,
because
very quickly we see as we go through the Torah that the Moabites now that they've come and settled
in the land that God brought them to according to Deuteronomy 2 the Moabites start worshipping
Kimosh the Moon God and other pagan gods and I saw some of that stuff for like I saw
Moabite texts on you know Qunaiiform tablets and shammish stuff at that museum I'm telling you guys
It's like a lotus beer's museum.
There I'm getting no
for this advertiser by the way.
Yeah, yeah.
I just had a very good time at the museum.
The British Museum is better.
The British Museum is farther away.
Yeah, it's possibly the greatest museum in the world.
Yeah, but much farther away.
Yes, a little more often.
And not guilt-free, given that everything there is kind of stolen.
Indeed. There's a whole like plaque or sign at the front of this museum here in Chicago
that
actually kind of apologizes on some level for the fact that they have a bunch of these artifacts.
But explains like the laws of the time had an arrangement where some artifacts were allowed to
those doing the excavations and then some were given to the host country. So it was like
sort of giving an explanation of like no we didn't steal all this stuff. We had to deal.
We had to deal. We had a licensing agreement.
Yeah, except in the terms of conditions.
So now Disney gets to
your wife anyway. Living here in 2024. Yeah. So yeah. So and as we mentioned, right, though,
right? So on the one hand, right, you see the Moabites once they settle. And this is of course the
big warning in Deuteronomy to the Israelites is that God telling them, not really warning them.
He's kind of just telling them what's going to happen. That once they come into the land and they
settle down and they plant their crops and they plant their vineyards and they're living in their
cities that they
forget about him. Yeah. Because they don't need him anymore. They're not dependent on him anymore.
They'll fall into the paganism right of the world. But even that is not a given. Because as we
mentioned before, Melchizedek is the king of a city. The city of Jerusalem. And he's keeping it real.
And he still is worshiping the true God. He's still worshiping Yahweh when Abraham gets there.
So it's not a forgotten conclusion.
and let's say he goes, we'll get a troll, but it's much clearly it's dangerous, right?
It's more difficult.
There's a tendency.
I have to say now, by the way, like this is the most already the most unusual Lord of
Spirit episode ever because instead of being by myself in a dark room, as I mentioned
earlier, I am seeing a cross from Trudy the Tank Richter, but I'm also now next to the
CEO of ancient faith ministries, Hori Melinda Johnson, who's waving in a vigorous way that
none of you can see.
but nonetheless it is true.
And so yes, this is a group effort here.
You have this feeling that you're being watched.
I am literally being watched and listened to.
And this is the most ridiculous thing ever
because everyone knows I'm the one
who needs the superficial.
No.
Like you're kind of fine on your own recognizance.
I'm the one who's gonna get us into trouble.
Clearly we can't trust your wife
to keep an eye on you.
I do this from the church.
She's not even here.
I don't think she even listens half the time.
She's done with me.
Like, I've heard you talk all day.
Like, I don't need any more of this.
Exactly.
This is my break.
I've heard of the church and talked to everyone else.
I've heard of all this, yeah.
Yeah, so.
Yes.
Yeah, I am, I am, can confirm.
Yeah, and Arkey and more waste than one.
I don't even have a plan.
So.
We talked about last time, right?
So that the axial age, there is the shift that happens also that sort of produces second
temple Judaism, right, that we see a shift from what's called Asian Israelite religion
after the exile, the return of the land.
product of things that happen to the exile product.
of the shift in status.
Yep, big focus on the Torah.
Like, yeah.
Josiah, all that stuff, everybody.
Josiah was way before this, but anyway.
Yes, yes, but yeah, but I mean, it's emblematic
of this idea, right?
Of this renewed focus on texts and so forth.
It's sort of, yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
But so, yeah, so after the return from exile,
now Judah is no longer an independent kingdom.
It's Judea, it's a Persian province.
Yep
a shadow of its former self.
Then a Greek, so you could province and then a Roman province.
But there's this shift where you get the emergence of the synagogue system that happens.
And the corresponding emphasis on texts and the public reading of texts and of scribble activity and copying and studying and mastering the texts.
And this then also this literacy emphasis then
also produce as an emphasis on putting things in writing.
So this is when you get this explosion
of second-time Jewish literature,
which is recording what was previously oral tradition
into these various texts,
these various documents around sort of around
and surrounding the Hebrew scriptures.
All this starts happening in the axiote,
but this is a shift in a trend
that affects everybody everywhere.
Yeah, right as we...
said in great detail last time. By the way, I have to share this with everybody. Someone
on the YouTube's, the tubes of you just asked the, I mean, very reasonable question, does
Trudy have entrance music? And when she is finally inducted into the WWE Hall of Fame,
and there's some kind of nook there in the exhibit that's dedicated to-
They don't have a physical hall of fame.
the tank Richter. Well, well, we
We have to, um, actually, yeah, have a physical, but they, well,
okay, a, a website, a topic of much controversy.
Will it play the music?
Like when you go and click on, you know, the, the tank, uh, exhibit.
Yeah.
I don't know what her music would be.
My entrance music is William Shatner's, uh, cover with Peter
Frampton of Spirit in the Sky.
That is my entrance music.
That is, but excellent.
Yes.
That is, and that's on YouTube, by the way.
Yes
on which song Frampton does indeed come alive.
I think I if I had to pick entrance music for myself,
it's an even toss up between Chibalmato's
Know Your Chicken and
Nerf Herders Van Halen.
I think that's where I'm today anyway.
I'm thinking they just play pomp and circumstance.
I won't do it.
I will tell you what we called it when I was in high school band
Because you're supervised I am supervised yeah, but I'm also much
Yeah, anyway, yeah, I'm much more restrained than than my very Reverend doctor co-host
That's not saying much very true
So yeah, so what what we didn't mention
Right
last time was that
The interesting fact that there are a bunch of critiques of the idea of the actual age.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So the term is used by everybody now.
Oh, by the way, your wife just weighed in on Facebook.
Oh, is she actually listening?
She said, there's the nights.
He's your responsibility.
Oh, there we go.
There we go.
She is officially, if caught or captured, she denies our knowledge of my activities.
has been transferred.
I mean, I get your action figures if something horrible happens to you.
No, I don't think you have other people.
They're probably laid out one by one in your will, I bet.
You wouldn't even clean them with candor or anything.
You would just leave them in a box or something.
Actually, what would happen is my wife would sell them on eBay.
There you go.
Say, it's true.
So um...
Yeah, so everybody uses the phrase the axiolage now to refer to the same thing or refer to
the same period.
Everybody might be a little broad.
Well, yes, everyone who's talking about it.
Yes, everyone who talks about it.
Right, right.
Those people don't talk about this that often.
Yeah, weirdly on the streets of Chicago today, even at the University of Chicago, I did
not hear people talking about the axiolage.
Yes, but everyone who talks about it calls it the axiolage.
They use that term.
who talks about the topic.
Yes, I realize that most people, unlike me, do not think about the Roman Empire every day,
but yeah.
But there was, especially it was first proposed, there was disagreement about it.
And there are still some people who kind of have an axe to grind who will use the freight,
like they'll put it in scare quotes, like the religious shifts of the axial age in scare
quotes.
because they don't want to say they fully buy it.
But where we're going here is one of the main criticisms,
possibly the most common and prominent criticism
of the idea of the axial age,
is that the axial age can't really be all that important
and can't really be the axial age,
as in this axis upon which things pivot.
I think turns out.
because
Christian
Christianity arises later.
Yeah, this has been one of the big criticisms. Okay, and
This assumes a couple of things, right number one, you can see why
We've spent a lot of time on this show
describing in
completely objective non-sarcastic terms
terms are 18th and 19th century German friends.
But, when the Axial Age is first being discussed and proposed by one of our early 20th century
German Swiss friends, you have to understand that academia, the circles in which he's
talking about this, are firmly entrenched in this developmental idea of religion, which
which of course is all leading up to 19th century German Lutheranism.
therefore sees the rise of Christianity as the most transformative event in world history.
Yeah, like the rise of a new kind of religion.
And I, yeah, not to just pop culture this out a little bit, but I recall not, not civilization
six, but there was an earlier iteration of civilization that as religion shows up in the game, like
different religions appear at different points and it completely uses this idea, this evolutionary
idea of religion.
Like there's earlier forms and then Christianity is like this almost last one.
Yeah, which is kind of a wacky thing to do for access games.
And it's this massive shift and assumed in there for reasons we've also talked about before,
that are related to the fact that they're Germans,
is this idea that there's this just incredible discontinuity between Christianity and preceding
Judaism.
Yeah, which I mean a lot of Christians buy that idea and they would see it. Yeah, right. Yes
And but they would and but I mean you know just to be as charitable as possible to them
Which I think is sort of my bit in the podcast but yeah
To be as terrible as possible
I think it's this idea that well Jesus appears on the scene and that changes everything right like there's new revelation that changes everything
Yeah, so it's understandable. It's understandable right
The problem is when you go past
that to demeaning the Torah, the Hebrew scripture, the Old Testament, marginalizing it.
Which no one in the Testament does.
Right.
Sorry, Martin Luther.
So but for our early 20th century scholarly friends on the international stage, they're
firmly indoctrinated into that, right, that the religion of the Pharisees was this dark
evil thing and Christianity is this complete no-vom complete
completely different, virtually, if not actually a different God.
Yeah. Right.
And so for them, again, they see this massive discontinuity,
and this massive discontinuity is after the axiolage,
so that all these shifts of the axiolage,
pale in comparison and can't be that important,
was sort of the criticism.
But, but, but, the critical assumptions in there are fundamentally wrong.
Yeah.
And the reason why we know that's the case is by looking closely at Second Temple Judaism.
Right. Yeah. And Second Temple Judaism's. The vast variety of forms Judaism took in the Second
Temple period and coming to the realization which fortunately even totally secular scholars,
Well, Christian scholars, Jewish scholars, non-religious scholars, right, of Christian origins.
I've pretty much all come around to now
that Christianity is a second temple Judaism.
Right?
It is a form of second temple Judaism.
Basically two forms of second temple Judaism,
Phariseism and Christianity,
which are closely related,
because Christianity is ultimately a variation
of Phariseism,
are the two forms of second temple Judaism
that survived the destruction of the second temple.
And are now rabbinic Judaism and Christianity respectively.
And one interesting thing that's come out of writing a recent book.
Oh, that's right everybody on the Internet.
There's a book coming out next week, everybody.
Yeah, yeah, which we've told some of you called St. Paul the Pharisee Jewish Apostle to the
Nations and that I've had some interesting discussions about with some
Jewish folks is that one of the places where you see how closely related
Pharisee Judaism and Christianity are is that both Christianity and the
Pharisees that becomes rabbinic Judaism both want to claim Gomalil.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
There are icons of him, by the way.
He's a saint in the Orthodox Church.
Amen.
And he's one of the most prominent rabbis in the...
the mission which is part of the Talmud.
More people need to name their kids after him.
Kamal Iol.
Yeah, that's a great name.
Yeah.
So, right, these are two closely allied second-table Judaism's
that being the two survivors then gradually split off
from each other.
Read, religion of the Apostles, find out all about that.
That's literally the introduction, I think, isn't it?
Yeah, that's kind of where we go.
Convert question. Yeah.
So Christianity, therefore since it is a form of second-temple Judaism, that means it is a continuation of second-temple Judaism.
Right. It is fundamentally the same thing.
Right. Now, that is not to say that the coming of Jesus as the Messiah is a small thing or unimportant.
Right, right.
Obviously.
It is the most important thing to ever happen in history, right?
But, but, but we're talking about something that was anticipated and expected and prophesied
and believed about for centuries beforehand within Second Temple Judaism.
Yeah, it didn't come out of nowhere, which is why Jesus very rightly is
Chiting people all the time like um hello
Yeah, you know that if you knew Moses you would
him right right and then Christianity's focus upon it is a reflection upon it having happened
right so yes you move from anticipation of this event happening to reflections upon this event
having happened but that's a passage of time right it's not a change in the religion yeah it's not
a new religion right so yes this temporal transition has happened right
But that's it.
And so the reason we took the time to come back
and do this here at the beginning of this episode,
which yes, technically we're still at the beginning
of this episode, as these things go for us.
That's true.
We're going to use, so there's this relationship then,
between second-templed Judaism and Christianity
that we just talked about, this relationship of continuity.
Within that continuity, there are things that change.
Like there's a new testament now.
There's, it's center, et cetera.
There are these things that change.
But there's this overarching continuity and not a break.
So we're gonna use this as sort of a paradigm
for understanding how you can have changes
and shifts of different sorts without breaking cotton.
Even within the history of Christianity per se.
Right.
Later, that's what we're going to apply this for.
Two, exactly.
Other such things.
Which I just want to underline this because, I mean, this is one of the fundamental assumptions.
Not just of this, you know, the hundred episodes we've done now, although it's super is.
But it really, like, really people, if you look closely
at the writings of the church,
fathers. If you look closely at the texts of the services of the Orthodox Church, this
assumption is everywhere. And I think if someone reads a radical discontinuity in this, honestly,
they're looking at it with Martin Luther eyes. That's what it is.
It's a serally Martin Luther, they could be Muslims.
No, there's that.
Exactly.
But yeah, I mean, it's this idea of, you know, that, that, that, that Torah is, is over in
some way, you know, which if that were true.
I mean, we actually had someone post something like this earlier in the, in our Facebook
group today, where they were quoting from St. Justin Martyr, who was talking about Deuteronomy
and was wondering like, is what he says here about Deuteronomy, you know, where he talks
about these things.
no longer bind you like is he basically saying like that the Torah is no longer an effect,
you know, because you could certainly read it that way, but that's frankly a very Protestant
reading.
Yeah.
Well, and even more common now, maybe just more common in the circles I hang around in,
but that's which are dodgy circles.
Deeply weird.
Yeah.
More parallelograms than circles, I would say.
More, more rhombus of a sort.
I'm sorry.
It's less of the Old Testament, New Testament, Discontinuity because I think, you know, I mean,
we settled this with Marcy and we settled this in the beginning of the second century.
Come on.
But there is still a lot among sort of out of date liberal scholars and Muslims.
this tab.
drive this wedge between Jesus and St. Paul. Oh yeah. That's doing two different things.
And that Christianity is this Pauline religion that St. Paul made up. Right. Right. Which also has
as a feature chucking the Torah in the bin. And this is not just an extended, you know,
pitch for your book that's coming out next week. No, it is not. But everyone should go ahead and
and by that book it comes out.
If you're interested in exploring this more,
but...
But yeah, of the two, I am the one of us least prone to self-shill.
That's true.
You're not even on the social medias anymore.
No.
Yeah.
Yeah, so that sort of attempt, right?
But yeah, so there is this great continuity, but that continuity is not denying that things
happened, that things that happened were important, right?
that there are the
various shifts. So to kind of break this down, since we're going to be using this as a paradigm,
right, we're going to be applying this to other things, right, what are the important points
of continuity that we're talking about? Where are the places where we need to have a kind of
continuity in order to say that there is an overall continuity despite other things may be shifting,
changing variant.
want. Yeah, and and how can you tell when something is in discontinuity? Right. And if one
of these things is broken, now we're talking about something else, right? A new religion.
Yeah. And this is, it is we apply this paradigm. We're going to be arguing not just like,
hey, father and daughter and I came up with this cool thing. We're essentially going to be arguing
that like as especially the early church fathers are addressing different groups, right?
This is
essentially the model they're implicitly using.
Not explicitly, like there's no church father who I can quote you who's gonna lay this
out exactly the way we're gonna lay it out.
Yeah, there's no like systematic formula.
But implicitly, right, you read St. Aaron AS against heresies, right?
You'll see him making arguments related to these points we're talking about.
vice versa, where do you think we're getting these points?
Anyway, so yeah, I'm surprised really folks instead of accusing we have never quoting
the church fathers, you should be accusing me of plagiarizing the church fathers for
using their stuff and not citing them.
How dare you, sir?
And if you do the church father's better, that's probably what you do.
So there is an idea.
It's all in public domain now by the way.
This is good to sound strange and foreign.
I notice some people, some Christian people.
That is the idea of primary and secondary scriptures.
And by that, I'm not referring to things
that are deuterocononical.
Right.
And I think the reason people aren't used to thinking
this way is because of the deep impact
that Solar Scriptura has made.
on the American culture and, you know, northern European culture more broadly where it's
spread throughout the world where scriptures are scriptures and everything that's not
scripture is not scripture. And that's it. Right. But this isn't the way scriptures
have functioned in the history of Judaism and Christianity. Right. There are primary and
secondary scriptures within the canon.
So it's pretty hard to argue and be taken seriously by anyone that the Torah doesn't occupy
a special place within Judaism, all the way through, right?
That it is in some way the primary scripture and then the rest of the Hebrew scriptures
are sort of secondary to it because they're all in different ways reflecting on
the contents of the Torah.
Yeah, commenting, applying,
regurgitating,
just reading through the lens of it,
or applying it, or interpreting.
Right, interpreting it.
Right.
Right, so you have this relationship.
And we have built into our liturgical forms,
a similar relationship within the New Testament.
Oh, sure.
I mean, just look at...
But set the content aside, just look at the way the gospels are treated in the services
and look at the way readings from the ex and the epistles are treated in the services.
Right.
It's not the same.
And yeah, and it's very obvious, right?
So we're walking into nothing about Christianity and they heard the one reading where someone
just gets up and does it.
Generally, the Orthodox Church, someone who's not even Orthodox can do the epithelian.
It's theoretically possible.
I know, I know there's a bunch of people clutching their pearls right now, but I will give
you an ancient example just so you can let go of those pearls so they can be passed on
to your grandchildren.
It was possible in the early, petristic period, actually, I had a T-Tee, but you know what
I'm talking about?
it's six century.
you tanser a catacumin as a reader.
Like the guy was designated as a reader,
and yet was not even a Christian,
a North-Earthrox Christian,
he not even baptized yet,
but he could be a liturgical reader in the services.
Now I'm not saying that we should do that now,
but I'm just saying that this is a thing, this is a thing.
Yes, and this is commonly done throughout the Orthodox world.
you
carried over from the fact that in synagogues,
guests are frequently invited to do the Haftora reading.
Yeah, the Torah reading.
A visitor.
Yeah.
Not the Torah reading.
Right, they don't get up there and touch the Torah scroll.
Okay.
Why about the Haftora reading?
A non-Jewish person, right?
And we've continued that trend.
And people sit for it.
Everyone stands for the gospel.
Only clergy read the gospel book.
There's a procession with the gospel book,
just like there was a procession with the torus.
in the middle of the altar.
Yeah, right. This is just the case.
Venerational Gospel book.
If the New Testament is working fundamentally the same way,
you have the Gospels of our Lord Jesus Christ,
and then you have the epistles,
which includes the Apostolic on, the Apostolic writings,
with all the rest of the New Testament writings,
which are interpreting and applying
The Birth Life Death Resurrection
ascension into heaven and the throne of Christ.
That's what they're doing.
It's what St. Paul says he's doing.
He's going out and preaching Christ and him crucified.
He's preaching the Gospel, he's preaching the contents of the Gospels.
This is why it's traditional for homilies in most cases to be about the Gospel reading.
Indeed, that's what the word means.
It means the same.
Literally, that's what it means in Greek is the same.
He's now gonna say the same thing.
but in different words.
Right.
And now that doesn't mean that they're not scriptures.
It just means that within the scriptures there are these relationships.
Yeah.
Right?
So Saint Peter already calls Saint Paul's writings scriptures.
Saint Paul's letters.
And that's why he's still alive.
While he's still alive, still writing them at the same time.
Right.
So how does that work?
Well, this gets into how Second Temple Jewish writing worked in general.
Second Temple Jewish writing in general, we talked about within the Second Temple period,
there's this burgeoning of all of these other texts around the scriptures that are putting
down in writing things that previously had been oral traditions surrounding the scriptures.
And these texts were read and used and were treated as
books by different communities. But they were always on the level of, here is how we interpret
and apply the Torah, in most cases, within our community. And so for St. Peter, looking at the way
St. Paul's letters were functioning within the Christian communities, the churches, at all of these
these different cities.
Right he saw them functioning as that kind of scripture. Yeah, he's not saying I am St. Peter and therefore I solemnly
Canonize the writings of my fellow Apostle
It doesn't give a list. Yeah, it's like oh, yes, I see you guys using them this way. It that's what they are right and so
He understands that's how a certain type of scripture is used
Right and so he
recognizes
recognize is that that is in keeping with right what what in in cumron the
Dead Sea Scrolls one category the text is sectarian text oh I saw a piece of
a Dead Sea Scroll today yeah it was really cool I said father Steven of photo
of it I was like ah it's a Dead Sea Scroll well fragment of one yeah yes yes
A bit, a bit, a bit.
Yeah.
A chunk.
Right, and the...
texts were for the organization of the community, right? So they had this category. And this
is an existing category. But those texts that are constitutive of the community, right,
they're how St. Paul's epistles are how those early Christian communities came to be organized
in terms of their leadership, in terms of their worship, in terms of their way of life.
All of these things are being organized in through these texts.
So this is...
one category of continuity, right?
Are we using the same texts?
This is why it's so important
that you don't throw out the Old Testament.
Because if you do throw out the Old Testament,
you're now a new religion, congratulations.
You're a Marcy Knight heretic.
You're not Judaism or Christianity, you're something else.
Yeah.
So having the same formative body of scriptures, right?
of scriptures.
Right?
is part of the continuity.
Yeah.
You also have a continuity of forms of worship, right?
Now people may point at this and say, people of certain
pen to say, well, wait a minute, second-templed Jewish
were a ship they're offering animal sacrifices in the temple.
And only there, only in that one geographic spot
Christianity isn't
doing that. We're not going to get into the whole argument about the Eucharist being
a sacrifice right now. Right. I've got a published journal article on that. Go read that.
Right. But a couple points about that things you may things you may not have heard actually.
So number one, there were already within Second Temple Judaism, forms of Second Temple
Judaism that were
We're doing temple things outside the temple in Jerusalem.
Everybody get up off the floor and now this is a little shocking.
Animal sacrifices going on in places.
There's the offering of incense.
Yeah, going on in places other than the temple in Jerusalem and it was not being like decried
spoken.
Yes, they were not being considered heretics and evil and everything else.
This was a thing, boys and girls.
So probably the most prominent one.
was the Jewish temple in Leontopolis, which was sort of on the outskirts, in modern
terms of suburb, but they didn't really have suburb near Alexandria in Egypt, which
is basically where most of the Alexandria and Jewish community was concentrated. What
was Leontopolis is now referred to as Tell Yehudi, the Hill of the Jews.
How about that?
Because there's still that connection there.
and there was a temple there to the God of Israel.
And it didn't even look like the temple of Jerusalem.
It was an obelisk.
I'm still trying to picture that in my head.
Like, how does that work?
Cause an obelisk is mostly like the Washington Monument.
Yeah, it's an obelisk.
They got a door in the bottom.
Okay.
Right. And the bottom floor is the temple proper.
Alright, there's two hanging layup
on either side of the door when you go in. It had been a temple to baste. The the cat god.
But when the Jewish community came to predominate in Leontopolis, they
turned it into a Jewish temple. And they justified it using the solemn verse that talks about
about there being an altar of incense to God in Egypt.
But also the way this worked,
that we do about...
this because Philo made use of this, Philo of Alexandria. The way it was viewed was not as a second
temple or a second second temple. A replacement for the temple of Jerusalem. Judaism 2.5. But it was
viewed as sort of an outpost of the temple in Jerusalem as connected to the temple. So that they
would still send money to Jerusalem to the temple. They would still go and make pilgrimage to Jerusalem
to the temple. But for sort of day to day.
stuff right because obviously you can't travel from Alexandria, Egypt to Jerusalem back
and forth right at this period in history.
Even too.
That is very difficult.
Yeah, but it's you couldn't do it very often then.
For day-to-day stuff, they would go to this one in in Leontopoulos right there also may
have been there's a lot of debate about this on elephantine island temperatures.
By the way, the temple in Lea Toppilus was actually the only...
only Jewish temple for three years.
The temple Jerusalem was destroyed in AD 73.
The one in Leontopolis was destroyed in AD 73.
And that was when the Roman Emperor ordered the governor to destroy it because he was worried
that with the temple in Jerusalem destroyed there in Alexandria, that might become a
rallying point for a further rebellion by the Jewish people.
So he had it destroyed three years later.
But for three years, that was the only function.
in the world. Sacrifices are still being offered.
Elephantine Island there may well have been a Jewish temple there as well.
Where is that? Exactly. Like that's...
Yeah. It's never been there.
It's an island in the stream. That's what we are.
Somewhere in between. Anyway.
I caught that reference. Thank you.
Thank you.
My boss is grinning over here, so she clearly caught it as well.
Yeah, so there's, yeah.
Basically, we discovered on the island, we know there were some Jews at the time of
the exile who went in that direction, who were there.
And there is a, the remains of the foundation are there.
And the foundation kind of matches the floor plan of Solomon's Temple with something that
could be a well of souls.
Oh, yeah.
I can hear you in the Jones.
sort of this anticipation that, well, this was probably,
you can't prove it.
I mean, if someone wants to say no, I mean,
But, and also part of what's poisoned the well
on why people want to deny it is that it gets used
at a lot of conspiracy theories
about where the Ark of the Covenant ended up.
Yeah, there's the will of souls thing.
Yeah.
So they say, like, oh, see, this proves they had the
Ark of the Covenant with them when they went to Egypt, right?
So anytime something like this.
It's used in conspiracy theories. Scholars are prone to just deny the whole thing on principle to not go there
But also not not sacrificial temple stuff
But non sacrificial temple stuff in terms of the worship that went on in the temple. Yeah, there's other things going on
was sort of adapted at cum rod
Hmm because they had rejected the second temple is corrupt. That's the Dead Sea scrolls it plays everybody
Right, they had...
adapted some of the thing. So, and then, right, so already you have people doing some of the temple stuff outside of the temple within second temple Judaism in some groups.
And then, conversely, we see in the book of Acts that Christians were still making animal sacrifices in the temple after Christ ascension, including Saint Paul and Saint James.
I thought we agreed not to talk about that.
Oh no, we've talked to him before!
It's kind of...
Yeah, no, it's this weird lacuna.
It doesn't fit the paradigm that a lot of people have
of these radical disjunctions.
Right, yeah, right.
And so what you actually see here again
in worship is a continuity.
From second temple Judaism
that Christianity adapts some elements of temple worship
in its worship, continues to use the temple
until the temple is destroyed
the temples destroy.
they go on with their worship, which is basically synagogue worship, plus some adapted temple worship element.
And I mean, and there's some other big elements too that get adapted like the structure of authority.
It's almost the same. It's almost the same in early Christianity as it gets translated differently.
Yeah. In your Old Testament and New Testament.
And when he says that, that's literally the case.
It's literal translation different.
But the words, like if you read the Old Testament in its Greek translation and you read the New Testament in Greek,
you'll see the same words getting used.
Right.
So when Ecclesia is church in the New Testament and assembly in the Old Testament.
Right. Whereas like in the Greek Old Testament, Ecclesia refers to the people of Israel.
Yes.
And Ecclesia is using the New Testament for the church, but they're just using the same word.
using the same word, the same word refer to the same group of people.
Yeah, but the same thing with right you have the elders of the people
the elders of Israel in the Old Testament and you have
Presbyters, which are not like same word. It's not like they're not analogous to the Sanhedrin.
They are the Sanhedrin. Yeah, the church. Yeah. Right. Right. And you have the shepherds of Israel.
I mean, dude, that means you and I have you and I are Sanhedrin.
Pass you have the Episcopie, you have the bishops, right? There's this direct...
carry over. Right. So these authority structures are fundamentally the same in both. Right.
And so this is a point of continuity between second-table Judaism and Christianity. Yep.
And then you have the ritual life in the calendar. Yep. Right. Many of the same feasts.
Where, right. The calendar originally, the original Christian calendar is just brought over
from Judaism.
Yep.
Right.
With both layers.
The apostles going to Jerusalem to celebrate the Passover, but what they're celebrating is the resurrection of Christ.
Right. Exactly.
And same thing with Pentecost, same thing with.
And then over time, distinctly Christian feasts get added.
Right. Like the martyrdom of St. Stephen is probably the first one.
And then the offenies probably the second one.
at one and so on.
And so now you might look at the Jewish calendar, the Christian calendar and say,
these are kind of our part. I see the connections, but you have to go back to the first century.
And do the comparison there. Right. And that's where you see this continuity. So
we just described and we've given this as an example. Right. There is
right, a form of second temple Judaism that becomes known as
Christianity first at Antioch.
And
Right, and it has continuity with the second temple Judaism that came before and
Ancient Israelite religion, even though if you look at like you come to a divine liturgy and you go on your time machine back to the tabernacle and the wilderness,
the two things you see are not going to be identical.
So we a lot less blood and my parish this Sunday, for example, not like last Sunday or
I'm sorry, I'm sorry, I'm sorry.
But there are, sorry.
Right?
But there's this continuity, but there are also shifts and movements, right?
And the passage of time, right?
And different social and cultural settings.
Yep.
Right?
So you can have this overarching continuity within these shifts and changes.
So that's where we're starting setting up this paradigm.
Now we're going to talk about in the next half.
After are we gonna have a clip we are gonna have a clip but before we do the clip
I'm not thrown to the clip yet
That is it clippy is it that little guy with the no
I think he was fired. I
Missed the little guy from I was never an MS word guy
the
But we're gonna we're gonna in the second half we're gonna take this kind of paradigm and and
and really show how this was applied.
Yeah, in the early church to a few different groups and then in the third half we'll get into how we might apply it today.
Yes indeed. So yes, so in honor of our 100th episode and our fourth anniversary, many of you have clamored for clips.
Is there a clip clamor?
There is a clip clamor from the, yeah, there is a clip clamor from the con clave of, see, I'm trying to come up with a further
but it's not going to be.
but Flip Clammer sounds like a really bad supporting character in a 1940s comic book.
Wow, I'm imagining, yeah, well done. Yeah, so many people have asked,
could you like create a clips channel or something like that? And who knows? Maybe I'll be able
to prevail upon Simon our manager of the tube of use to do that at some point, but in honor of
this 100th episode this this sentence
of Lord of Spirits.
We have put together a few clips
that we think you might enjoy.
And so I'm gonna ask Trudy the Tank Rector
to play the first of these three clips
and then we're gonna go ahead and take our first break.
And if you don't enjoy them, too bad, the show's free.
Too bad. No one's making a list of this.
What are you doing here?
Show's free.
Get what you pay for.
What's all this hate listening is going on?
Anyway, all right.
Take us, give us the dream.
up there, Trudy.
So, how do you interact more with your angel?
Well, number one, a lot of prayer books, for instance, will have a prayer in there called
the prayer to your guardian angel.
If you don't have it in your prayer book, then you could probably find an orthodox prayer
to the angel online somewhere.
I'm sure that you can find something.
And that's something that I went incorporate into your prayer every day.
But one of the things that actually, I don't know why I started to think that I was
doing this not that long ago I'm kind of ashamed to admit within just the past couple of years.
As I'm going to sleep, first of course we pray to our Lord Jesus Christ to preserve us and to
to save us, of course because we could die in our sleep. But also the next thing that I do then
is I specifically say, guardian of my soul and body, protect from me from all assaults of the evil
one this night. And then I also add, because I'm a husband and a father, protect my wife and my
my children and I name them in that prayer as
going to sleep because you go to sleep, that's a kind of a vulnerable position to be in, and you want
the guards up and doing their task in the night while you're asleep. And that is one of the things that
we know that the angels do. That's not all that they're about, for sure. We're going to be talking a
lot more on this show about what angels are about and what they do. One of the things that they do,
of course is to guard us. They keep us from harm, not just physical harm, but also
spiritual harm, like there is a war going on.
There is a war going on.
It is a spiritual reality, and we're participating in it.
We're either participating in the works of God
and becoming more like him,
or we're participating in the works
of the devil and becoming more like him.
Like the biggest aha moments in my conversations
with Father Stephen was when he said,
you know there's basically a thing
that's the opposite of theosis.
I said, what is that demonosis?
And he's like, well, I don't know
there's a word for it specifically.
But there is like you
participate in what God is doing and you become like him.
But if you participate in what the dark powers are doing,
you become like them, right?
So it's you're always headed in one direction or the other.
You don't get to stand still.
How do we participate in the reality of our angels?
I mean, prayer is the biggest thing, but also just have that sense.
I think especially when you're going to sleep is a good one.
But also, you know, when you wake up in the morning to say,
help me today.
Be with me.
We're not talking about some kind of flim flammy.
I hope angels are watching over you.
Like that's okay to see.
that, right? But that's kind of not all that they're really about. These are God's armies,
His created beings, their His government, in a very real sense. And part of our task is to become
like them. The Lord says that the sons of the resurrection, this isn't and Luke's gospel,
sons of the resurrection become like sons of God and equal to the angels. So we, we bequeat
take on their roles. We do the things that they do. You're, you're, you're guardian angel,
your patron saint, the one you're named after, the
one who's assigned to your parish is very concerned
with the place that your church is in.
The beginning is just to acknowledge that.
Like they're here, my church is just named after,
here in the Mayas, our church is named for the Apostle Paul.
It's not just named after the Apostle Paul.
He's here and this place is important to him
because we asked God to assign him here
and so we believe that that happened.
Love that dream harp, huh?
Man, you used to drink a lot.
a lot of caffeine.
Yeah, your amps are like an 11 minute.
That's true.
Yeah, it's true.
All right, people, well, we're going to go ahead and take our first break.
But give us a ring.
And like I said, since there's no screening of cause tonight, we're just doing it raw,
with no processing here in the studio.
So give us a ring.
to talk to you about whatever is on your mind.
So.
We're going to take our first break and we'll be right back with this 100th episode of The Lord of Spirits.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
The existence
of fools for Christ in the Orthodox tradition mystifies many people, even some within the
Orthodox Church itself.
People often wonder what purpose these sometimes comical and often times tragically misunderstood
saints serve in the life of the Church, especially given their unconventional and seemingly
bizarre behaviors.
In holy fools by Oswin Craten, we begin to gain a better understanding of these saints
curious manner.
of serving Christ as we learn about the extraordinary lives of 20 of the most well-known fools for
Christ in a series of brief hagiographies.
Available now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung. If you have a question call now at 855-237.
2, 3, 4, 6. That's 855 AF radio.
Hey, we're back. Thanks for that voice of Steve.
I don't know, can we just hang up perhaps
since we've done a hundred episodes by the end of this evening?
What do you think, Father?
I mean, maybe.
Maybe.
I mean, I had people ask me whether the last episode was the last episode.
And it was.
We could have a surprise last episode.
you know I want to have a surprise.
last episode, I'll law. I know the last issue of the Walking Dead, but cooler heads will probably
that's right. Most of us are not as frankly mean as you are. Yeah. Right. You know, last
episode. I talked about Richard Rollins and sort of bizarre attempts to.
Combine white rastafarianism and orthodoxy in his own person. I
Feel like now that we're more than six months out from Pazzo fast some of these stories can be told
What did Jordan Peterson say to you and no one else was listening well, we'll get that but okay
Okay, I was thinking today when I was thinking about today was like that was the first time I met
Pazzo in person oh
right he's not as large as you are you like you are three
Pejos, Ebenebri.
People are.
Yeah.
But so, you know, first time I met him in person and, you know, he was a little odd too.
Maybe not as odd as Ricky, but, um, so behind the venue, right, they had this sort of
camper or RV thing, like really nice, that was there for like the speakers and stuff
when they wanted to go hide they had like water and snacks in there.
right when they needed a break.
And so at one point, like we're all trying to find Pazzo.
Like where is Pazzo?
Right. And finally, a couple of us, we go into this RV.
And he's all the way back at the back of the RV.
And he's got like 18 different colors of Post-it notes.
He's got them all stuck to the wall in this weird pattern.
And he's like moving them around, right?
Sort of muttering to himself.
See, pushpins.
And so we want, no, no, just post it, no.
Just post it, no, it's okay.
And we go up to him, we say, Jonathan, what are you doing?
And he turns around at us, and he's just wild eyed.
And just keeps screaming at us, this is art.
This is art.
And we kind of fled out of the RV, right?
And waited for about that.
He was in there another 40.
I don't know what was going on, but I just thought our listeners might like some of these
true stories behind the scenes at Pajot Fest.
I'm floored.
I mean, I don't know what to do with that.
Is it because he's Canadian or...
See, I don't know.
I don't know the culture.
Yeah.
Right.
I mean, the cage is, of course, got thrown out of.
Oh.
like half Canadian or whatever.
She's saying it's not because he's Canadian.
Okay.
Like she's claiming that.
But we actually apparently do have a caller, unless she just accidentally hung up on this
person, I don't know.
So we're going to go ahead and take a caller.
A caller, I have no idea what your name is or where you're calling from because again,
we're doing this completely off the cuff.
So if this is Pat Jo, please explain the post it knows.
Welcome to the Lotus Speared podcast.
Oh thanks buddy.
David, I'm calling actually from Portland, Indiana.
Your name is David?
Yeah, actually, that's my, I was baptized in 2022.
So I've called in, I was one of,
when you had the episode of a panoply of bands,
I was like three of them.
Nice.
I do remember the panoply of bands.
Yes.
So three of those were my questions, but now I don't know.
I try to remember my David or my Benjamin, I don't know.
This is great because this is a good anniversary episode call.
Yeah, that like a call back here. That's right. Well welcome back Benjamin David
Yeah, this sounds like internist scene, you know early Jewish tribal fighting. So this is great. This is perfect. Yeah
Well, so speaking of the hopefully it's not actual outright inner fighting, but I
You know, I listened to father Dionne's conversation with a certain reformed
and a friend of mine recently got his book about the history of the church.
stuff. So I gave him Father Damek Eur, orthodoxy and heterodoxy to think like, hey, there's
another way of looking at church history because I haven't read the other book.
But yeah, so I did watch one of this guy's video about kind of like, I think he was talking
about the infallibility of the scriptures and he was going in a bit about what it's the
I will say about tradition, like there's a couple of verses in you saying, well,
basically we have no idea what those traditions were when he was talking about holding fast
to the traditions.
But he kept like, wow, what a punt.
Wow.
Yeah.
So because I was trying to watch a video on the half of dialogue with my friend, but he kept
talking about like the infallibility of the scriptures and stuff.
And so I just, you know, that being presupposed as I'm kind of transitioning out of, you know,
a Protestant world view and into an Orthodox one.
I was kind of, you know, on ditching the solar.
But I don't kind of understand where things land now with infallibility and that kind of stuff
So I was wondering if you guys could kind of expand on that idea and like kind of
Because I don't even remember like I didn't pay enough attention when I was in Bible college about
Kind of that whole target of the why it became so important to discuss them being infallible because I actually was listening to father
Evan Armitoss on one of his
I want to ask his orthodoxy live or his Bible study by King.
talked to something about he had like a total side comment about that might cause
the issue because he said that we don't necessarily hold to the idea or at least
the process under senior infallibility of the scripture. So I'll shut up and
listen now. Yeah. Even I'm not mean enough to get in a fight with father
Evan. I've met father Evan in person. He is very fit like he's ridiculously fit.
And, and so even a behemoth slash ogre like yourself, father's
is in everything my man. I don't know he might know some techniques. I'm just throwing that out there.
I'm just throwing that out there. But it would be like beating up the kindly old man at the grocery store.
He is rather nice. I couldn't fight him. He's rather nice. Yeah. Yeah. As we were saying earlier,
he's so nice that he makes me look like you. Yeah. It's true. Yeah. This is a great question. And I think
Thank you.
you know, speaking as someone who once,
once long ago in the before times was an evangelical,
although I'm very happy like a couple of years ago,
the number of years that I was Orthodox
has now passed up the number of years
that I was evangelical, which means I'm no longer a convert.
Right?
I think that the reason why there's this push
for infallibility, this understanding of
that description.
need to be understood in terms of this category of infallibility is because this is understood as kind
of a guarantee of their truth. Like this is the foundation on which the Protestant understanding,
and I know I'm generalizing here, but this is generally true. The Protestant understanding of
Christianity is as is the foundation on which it's built. And if you poke holes in the reliability of the Bible.
then you have a foundational problem.
Right?
So the category of infallibility is really a philosophical, logical category.
That there are no errors of any kind.
There are no discrepancies of any kind within the text of the Scriptures.
And that's how you know that they're correct.
Whereas, I would say that the Orthodox understanding of the Scriptures is, I wouldn't say that they're
fallible, right? That's the problem is this duality of fallibility versus infallibility. That's
part of the problem is that whole structure, right? But they are true. And the way in which they are
true is the way in which they function within the community of the church. And I'll also just
add, I mean, right before Father Stephen gives his um actually's and, you know, but did you ever consider this?
I'll also add that we've done a few episodes that are related to this question of how you know the
script, how you understand the truth of the scriptures. And the one that I think is the best place to
start is one that we did that was called, oh man, I'm blanking on the title. You know what I'm talking about,
father um the how and how not to read the bible yes how and
how not to read the Bible.
I think that that's really important.
And it was, I mean, it was a big learning experience for me
because it really gave me a very strong sense
of the way that the scriptures are really received
within the church.
And then we had, if another one calls something like house,
how you know stuff is true or something like that.
I don't remember exactly now.
But yeah, that's what I would say is,
is this problem?
of infallibility is it's taking a philosophical, logical structure and placing that on top of the
Bible. And the big problem with that, of course, is that it's essentially, it's assuming that there's
this other standard by which what God has given is measurable, which actually puts something above
above God himself, right? You know, if God is being measured against something, then shouldn't you
worship that something because that's clearly higher than God.
You know?
Father?
Yeah, I...
Actually...
Alright, good. Thank you.
You kind of confused an erancy and infelloviz.
Oh, did I?
Oh, well, yeah, okay.
Help me out.
See, I didn't go to Bible College either.
The core...
The core problem here is with the idea that a text can exercise a authority.
Which is logically impossible.
Right, cause it doesn't talk.
like a book doesn't sit up and say stop all that.
The point, are we talking about Gavin Orland?
Yeah, I was going to let you do it.
So it's being very circumspect.
The point Orland is making there is logically incoherent.
Right?
I didn't follow what he was doing.
I was like, wait, this is a thing to be missing.
The point, there's some problems here, but I couldn't put my finger on some of them.
But okay.
Yeah, and here's why it's logically incoherent.
A text can be authoritative.
It could be...
regarded as an authoritative text. A community can attribute authority to a text.
This text is authoritative for us. But the text can't exercise that authority because it can't do
anything. It sits on a shelf. It's not an agent. It can't act a written text. A person has to read it,
interpret it, and then act based on their reading and their interpretation. And so there's this
a physiological problem at the core of Solicitora, which is you don't have any access to the contents of scripture outside of your actually sitting down and reading the scriptures in time and space.
Right? Which means even if you want to say, let's yield all the points.
It's an era and infallible in the sense that the wildest evangelical fundamentalist thinks.
right? That doesn't get you anywhere because as soon as I have to read it and
it, I'm fallible. Yeah. So my sin, right? And this is especially pointed if you're one of those
folks who believes in total depravity. My sin is going to corrupt the holy text that I read.
And twist it. Remember we're talking about Peter talking about say Paul's epistles, right?
And many things in them that are hard to understand and people twist them to their own destruction.
right?
Like that's gonna happen, right? So therefore it being infallible and inherent is irrelevant to the situation
Right for the authoritative script text of scripture to function authoritatively within the church, right for
scripture to have any role in the life of the church there has to be
some kind of
infallible
context
In which the scriptures are read and interpreted.
Yeah, right there has to be some way in which I can know
That the interpretations of the text that I'm hearing are not just something that a sinful human came up with
Right because I'm not really hearing the the text
Even if I read it in the original language even if I go and read the New Testament in Greek
I learned Greek from a textbook that was written by somebody and I'm using a lexical
there was composed by somebody who had his own biases. There is no brute Bible,
there is a brute fact of the text of Scripture. It's all been interpreted.
And so the question, you can't avoid this issue. Right? Orton is interpreting the Scriptures
within the Reformed Tradition. I interpret the Scriptures within the Orthodox Tradition.
there
There is no difference, right, epistemologically between how we actually approach the scriptures
when we do it.
He won't admit it, maybe.
He's just reading what it says.
He's approaching it from within the Reform tradition.
I can play that game too.
I can say I'm just repeating what it says, right?
But I'm reading it in the Orthodox tradition.
How do we decide which of those two is correct?
Yeah, yeah.
So that's the relativism stuff that I kind of try to deal with with some of my friends on.
because that'll be one of the itself points out,
it's like, well, how do you know
if the least you're talking to anybody
and trying to, you know,
or, you know, give interpretation on the scriptures.
So, you know, some of them,
like the kids say, crashed out.
Yeah, and just, by the way,
I was just to correct myself,
at least according to the various things that I looked up,
yes, you're right, father,
I did collapse in fallibility with an air and sea.
In fallibility is the idea that you can't make a mistake.
An air and sea means that there are no mistakes.
All right.
which i mean it's it's funny to think like how can a book be infallible
like it doesn't
do stuff right they're tributing agency to yeah
there's a scripture is the soul authority like it functions it doesn't
yet doesn't work sit on a throne and make core pronouncements yeah the core issue
is not so the scripture the core issue is ecclesiology
yeah
yeah that's the core issue
right and this is
what i tried to tell
The Catec humans, the inquirers who come to...
my parish, right, is there's only one reason to join the Orthodox Church.
You come here and you find Christ here.
And if you come to the conclusion that Christ is here and this is Christ's Church, then
whatever the Church is teaching, if this is Christ's Church, is the true.
Yep.
All right, and then you try to explore it and understand it, and that's what we're doing
on this show for the last four years.
trying to explore and understand and teach what it is that the church teed.
four years man we were in our mid 40s
I was pushing 50 we were slightly younger than
Patrick Stewart was at the beginning of star-checking next generation
But neither was where's the two pay that's yeah, well, I don't think you need a two pay
I could I don't need one but I am losing my hair on top
Yeah, Melinda's is shaking your head like please don't get a two pay
This is what you did into a torture this is what clerical clerical headgear is for everybody
Thank you.
Thank you very much for that call David. We're gonna go ahead and move on to our next caller again. I have no idea who you are caller but welcome to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Hello, can you hear me? We hear you.
Oh, Father. Hi. Christ is in our midst.
He isn't always so be what's your name?
It's Father Tim Karrin calling from Cape Cod.
Father Tim Karrin.
We've met in person before haven't we but it's I feel like it's been a long time.
many, many moons ago in Pennsylvania yet.
Oh man. How are you?
Yeah. I'm a little under the weather today, but so by your prayers.
But thanks for taking my call. I had an interesting one. I thought I would run by you guys on the show.
Okay.
on my community on here on Cape Cod.
I have a lot of people who are from Macedonia.
And oh man are we gonna have the whole messadonian thing?
I'm just putting it out there
They introduced themselves to me as messadonian. Okay
So I was wondering if either of you have had any experience with this and what a good
What you think might be a good pastoral redirected but are either you familiar with the phenomenon of kerbania?
Oh, yes
Okay. Yeah. So I've had a couple of requests for things like this. Yeah. I wasn't really
sure. But briefly to explain the people who aren't familiar with it. Yeah, because there's
going to be people who haven't heard of this and they're going to freak out as soon as
you start talking about it, Father. Most likely. Right. So that's okay. Because this show
we freak people out sometimes.
So apparently, priests in some Balkan countries and isolated places will still do animal sacrifices.
Sorta.
It was given to me to understand.
This was not early news to me.
Something that looks a lot like it.
It has certain similarities, but also really, really important differences.
But also we're going to go ahead and say this is bad and it should not.
be done. Okay, that's important. Yes. Yes. I was wondering what you thought would be a good
pastoral redirect to kind of recenter what it is we're trying to do and get away from the
honestly, I don't know where it comes from. If this is from a, it must be from a pre-Christian
understanding of animal sacrifice.
Honestly, honestly, I think it is a
Muslim influence. Honestly, because all the areas that it's done were part of the Ottoman
Empire. Yes, yes, just because there's correlation doesn't mean causation, but that's my sense.
That's my sense. Islam does practice. A form of animal sacrifice.
And if you compare the two, they are very similar. They're very similar. Yeah, it should be
So okay, so what is actually being done? This is my understanding of what what happened
in this custom is that an animal live animal is brought in and often they're like brought into the
church and kind of paraded in front of the account of Stasas and then brought outside and slaughtered and
cooked in eaten right and so there's some people that say sea sea animal sacrifice animal sacrifice
but important discontinuity as anyone who's been listening this show for any period of time will know
the thing is not being cut up on a prosthesis
table and it is not being put in an altar and it is not being burned to a God, right? So it is not
traditional animal sacrifice. It does look like some Muslim rituals. So, you know, like the
the the core elements right are the idea that people want to have a a festival meal and they want
want it to be blessed. And I think that like those things are good. Like that's good.
Right? But I think though that this idea of what it is that they're doing, especially bringing the animal into the church, which of course is expressly forbidden.
And the cannons of the Orthodox Church expressly forbidden. Preslizing for this reason because it's like, wait a minute, what are you going to do with that thing when you bring it in there?
You know, now they're not. They're not actually sacrificing it on the altar, right? They're not.
But it looks kind of
like they're about to, you know, is part of what's going on. So yeah, I think the thing
to do would be to to talk to people and say, look, and you know, you can't gather them
all together and say, now this is what we're going to be doing. But maybe find the people
that are part of that community that are receptive to conversation and to having their understanding
stretched a little bit and say, look, what is it that you're looking for out of this?
Like what is the thing that makes this?
wonderful and meaningful and powerful for you.
It's probably not bringing that goat into the building.
Probably not.
There's a lot more liturgically involved
than I envision, Father, that your description of it is.
That's my understanding of what it is.
And I'm sure there's variations because as you said,
it's remote. It's like it says, little village mountain practice.
This is not official. This is not something that bishops are condoning.
and I know that I know of bishops that have
that have said don't do this.
You know, it's not happening here in the US
as far as I know.
I don't know maybe your Macedonians are doing this
or would like to do it or whatever,
although I'm sure you would know if a goat had entered
the church building.
I should probably say that I've never
ascended to doing this for anybody.
Good.
I always tried to redirect.
Yeah, I mean, I think my feeling...
Probably for most people the big meaningful bit is everybody sitting down and eating the thing.
And I mean, you know, whether it's goat or lamb or whatever, I'm on board with that.
Absolutely.
Yeah, and yeah, there is, I mean, there are some, again, there's certain similarities to some stuff that Muslims do.
But Muslims aren't, as far as I know, they aren't putting animals on altars and killing them.
Are they doing that, Father? Do you know that? If Father Stephen?
If who's doing it if Moses
are doing that, putting animals on altars?
Well, they don't really have altars per set.
That's why I say it's very similar to the Muslim thing is very similar to this and that.
It's not totally.
And I know some people...
The sacrifice of the ancient sets.
Like some people, like I can't even shop at a halal butcher because you know, but the
truth is that like what constitutes halal butchering, I'll tell you what constitutes halal butchering.
It is a particular technique.
of cutting the throat of an animal and saying Bismillah while you do it, which simply means in the name of God.
That's all that that means.
Obviously that Muslims understanding God is very different from mine.
But I mean, someone wants to say in the name of God, while they slaughter an animal, I don't have personally have an objection to that.
But in any event, I'm going to say a lot of other prayers over that animal that's going to do it, what I needed to do, spiritually speaking.
So I don't know anything to add or subtract or multiply or divide.
Father Steve.
I mean, if it was me, I would just go and say the prayers and bless their livestock and
then eat a nice meal with them.
Right.
That sounds lovely.
Pretty straightforward.
Yeah, go bless with a bunch of holy water, sing pretty.
There's the book of knees.
We can bless all that stuff.
So yeah.
Right.
Yeah, exactly.
Oh
Well, that is helpful for this.
Thank you.
I was imagining that this was some kind of holdover
from pagan time and didn't consider that it might have been.
People say that, but I don't think that's true,
especially because it's not, again,
there's not.
It's too far off.
Yeah.
And it's too similar to stuff that's going on in Islam.
And in regions where Islam was very present.
So.
Right, right.
Again, I haven't done the research to see
there is an actual, you know.
causative relationship, you know there where you can actually really trace it to most impractices, but that is my shooting from the hip
Educated guests. So yeah, all right nice to hear from you with Father Timothy
Yeah, likewise. Thank you. Thanks for calling. All right. We're gonna take one more caller and then roll on with the second half of Lord of the Spirit. So
Welcome caller whoever you are speaking in the darkness out there somewhere
Are you there?
Hello?
Can you hear me?
We...
hear you. Who are you? Hello, my name is Levi. Levi? Yes. Yeah. We've had two tribes of Israel
so far tonight. That's right. Hi, yeah. Excellent. Well, thanks for taking my call. I've been listening
to you guys for a while. A few years now. I really appreciate the show. I've learned so much.
Thank God. Thank God. What's on your mind, Levi? I have a, well, I've got a question. I'm not even
exactly sure how to how to
I might kind of stumble through this question here, but I recently read, I'll start with some
background. I read the space trilogy or the Rant's Entryology by CS Lewis with a few
of my friends and kind of been talking about some of those really interesting ideas there.
And then also, I'm also a Peugeot Vian, I guess you'd say I follow a lot of his stuff and
some of those themes that I've heard him talk about.
Something that Lewis talked about is...
is like I guess I don't exactly know how to pronounce it like lograce or
lograce is like lograce yes that's the mythical yeah that is the the mythical
name of the realm that King Arthur rules right okay and it seems like he
talks about like almost like it's like the spirit of the of the nation or the
people yes the spiritual England yeah right so I guess my question is it
Does that represent?
Is that represents something, for example, is that something real and is that something
that's more like a collective consciousness or a collective soul of the people?
Or is it rather more like, is there something like a spirit or I guess an angel that goes
with a nation?
And if so, is it necessarily a good spirit or is it could it be that, like is it demonic,
Or is it one or the other or is it just not?
at all I guess. Yeah. When I make after you make sense. Wow I didn't get no I'd get to do our modern
Arthurian literary criticism tonight on Laura's Spirits Pathcans but yay he is happier than I was when I got
the Twin Peaks question. I'm still I'm still I'm still I'm still processing that night.
Okay.
Um, so, okay.
So obviously that comes up mostly.
within that hideous strength, which is the third and final novel, the one that will make you go,
what am I reading? Brilliant work. It's a sort of take on the Tower of Babel actually.
So, I mean, the concept of Logus as it functions within that novel, which, you know, Lewis is
he's taking a theme that does exist within our Thurian literature and kind of doing his own take
it. Okay? So it's it's it's it's it's it's own sort of refined, rarefied version of this.
All right. Like if you read Mallory, that's not there. If you read, you know, some of the stuff
from middle English, it's you're not going to see it there. Okay. And definitely not. If you see
if you read the Mavenogian, like if you read the, you know, well, original ish, well,
versions of these stories, it's not there. But in Lewis's version, Logris is kind of this
Ideal spiritual Christian England.
That's kind of present in a certain way.
It's sort of like England as it should be.
It's an eschatological England.
Yeah, yeah, that's what's going on.
So it's not,
you know, it's the idea of England as ruled by King Arthur.
You know, everything in its proper place,
all the nights of Camelot doing what they're supposed to be doing,
all that sort of stuff.
And so, you know, that he is strength, of course,
takes place.
in the modern period. And so therefore it's very much this kind of mythological England also.
But it's breaking in. Is the idea, I mean, Mirlin shows up in the story. All that kind of stuff.
There's this merging together of Arthurian myth and 1940s England. I mean, it's wild, wild stuff.
as you know, for well. But yeah, it's this idea of England as it should be.
England as it kind of could be, as a re-Christianized England.
It's not just nostalgia, like things used to be so great back in the day.
It's not just that, because the idea is that can be this present reality, but it is thoroughly
Christian in its character.
It's not utopian.
So yeah, that's what the way that the concept works in the book.
And you know, whether that's like a good idea, I mean, I think it works very well within the framework of the book. It's necessary within the framework of the book because it's contrasted against the civilization that
I'm forgetting the acronym now off the top of my head.
And any of them.
I see.
Yes, yes, the nice and I see.
I know they're so nice.
It contrasts against this sort of tower of Babel civilization, right?
So it's...
this sort of city of God, city of man kind of thing going on.
You know, like there's all, it's building on a whole long tradition that, you know,
goes back to St. Augustine Frank and the scripture is honestly, you know.
So it's that.
That's what's going on there.
Have you read that book, Father Stephen?
I have, but I have no real opinions on Zeus.
There you go.
I will tell you though because I'm re-reading it right now.
If you really want...
to read the highest and best of Lewis's fiction, till we have faces, is the one to read. And I will
say to everybody out there in Lord of Spirits land, I'm going to suggest you all read that as a kind of
catacetical companion. Because the way that it presents and deals with religion, I think is something
that we could all kind of stand to understand a little bit better.
So just putting that out there for everybody till we have faces.
All right, thanks very much for calling Levi.
Yeah, thank you.
I appreciate your time answering.
Appreciate you guys.
Absolutely.
All right.
So where are we father in this grand scheme of hearts?
Are we doing another clip or are we going to this?
Uh, I mean, yeah, sure.
Was play clip number two right now.
Hey, yeah, let's do all right.
Let's hear that dream harp there, Judy.
You know, nerdery aside and I clearly M1 because I consider reading, you know, eukaryotic
ritual texts and picking through Esau's genealogy to be fun and exciting ways to spend
an afternoon.
But beyond that nerdery, why is this important at all?
Right?
Why is this important to the orthodox faith or theology?
just, hey, it's interesting and fun and neat. I think this actually goes to the core, what
we've been talking about today. It goes to the core of what salvation is. And here's how
I think that is. My father used to tell me about my grandfather that at one point my father
was watching the Nurember trials on television which
were the trials of Nazi war criminals.
So sort of the most demonically evil humans
of our era.
And my father asked my grandfather
what he thought about, what had happened
in these trials.
And my grandfather's response was there
but for the grace of God, go I.
And usually when we say that we
say that about some misfortune someone has suffered someone has ended up homeless someone has ended up bankrupt
Someone has
Died at a young age we say oh there for the grace of god go. I it's god's grace that I have the things I have and that's not untrue
But my grandfather was saying that about
becoming a Nazi war criminal
He was saying that about becoming this sort of immoral monster
Who would murder other people in mass
and do these other things.
And this is how the scriptures present the demonic and our sin as participation in the
demonic.
After Adam and Eve have disobeyed, God says it's not good that man should live forever.
Because if we had, if we'd live forever in that state, we would have been just like the
demons, immortal and immortal.
mortal and evil. And so God gives us this life in this world and our mortality and our
repentance to prevent us from suffering that fate. A lot of times our Western Christian
friends present salvation as well, God has these laws. We've broken those laws. So he's
angry at us or he's compelled.
by his attribute of justice, he has to punish those violations of the law. And so Christ
comes to save us from that. So God has to save us from himself or save us from one of his
attributes, save us from his own justice. That's how the scriptures say. The scriptures
say that Christ came to save us from our sins because our sins are destroying us.
sins are turning us into these demonic monsters if we keep going down.
that path. So the truth we have here when we look at these giants who are the far end of where
that road leads, who represent someone not become like God but become like the demons, dehumanized
and inhuman, we see where the path of sin leads. And it shows us that in reality, Christ came to save
us from ourselves. And it gives us a clarity of...
of exactly what that means. So I think this is important beyond all the history and the tying
things together in the Old Testament and understanding some of the hymns of the church.
That's the core. That's the core. That despite our sin and wickedness, which is deliberate,
despite our throwing in our lot with these demonic spirits who rebel against and hate God,
Christ still loved us enough to come and die and rest.
us, redeem us and buy us back so that we could become sons of God as we've talked about
in previous episodes.
This shows us the other side.
We talked about past episodes, what we're saved to, what we're saved for.
This is what we're saved from.
There you go.
That old testnet.
I have no memory of ever saying that.
That may have been an AI-generated clip.
Also I had eight fingers on my left hand in that clip.
I know people at home couldn't see, but can confirm.
I think this is the first time we've gone two hours
before we've gotten actually begun the content
of the second half.
Oh yeah, yeah, it's off the rails.
I don't know if your keepers are gonna stay in the car.
I know, I know, like there's gonna be a point
where literally like trees just gonna walk out
and turn the lights off and I'm gonna have to figure out
I throw all this stuff off with you in the night.
Or we could just keep going.
Just keep going.
Broadcast a thaw.
That's right.
We could have a big telethaw and do a bunch of fundraising.
I would totally do 24 hours, a 24 hour straight.
Live show to raise money for something.
Wow, that would get so like punch drunk weird at the end.
Probably just four or five hours in, actually.
Say nothing about 24 hours in.
Are you at the point, your old age, where
you need to sleep every four or five hours?
Yeah, I mean, I'm still getting up.
I mean, I'm getting up multiple times a night, you know, so.
Yeah.
Oh yeah, you're doing that thing.
No.
Many such cases.
I know they say sleep like a baby.
I'm like, what, waking up screaming every two hours?
Because that's what I remember that was all like.
In your poor life.
Um.
Yeah.
So yeah.
Now we're going to actually start our second half two hours in.
When you, by the way, when you suggested doing a 24 hour
telethon. Melinda set up and she's like start
You could see the wheel is turning in her head like wait wait we can do this we can and it's like I will totally do it
You can rotate out co-host if father Andrew is gonna chicken out
Go full like happy days dance marathon episode
I'll be doing like the Russian dance at the end just to stay away you are an award-winning ballroom dancer. Yes, so
So that's not made up by the way, Melinda.
That's not made up.
He is an award winning.
Yeah.
Y'all, if you want to learn some weird secrets,
and they're all true about the life
of the very Reverend Doctor,
heptomaster, is it heptomaster, sex-domaster?
How many, how many master's degrees do you have?
Well, I got another one coming to the mail right now.
Is that number six?
I think.
Yeah, sex-domaster, Stephen DeYoung,
I know that sounds bad.
But that would be what it is.
You better hurry up and get another one so you can be ahead.
Or you're in some circle.
Yeah, you better hurry up and get another one so you can be the heptomaster.
Because that has happened and that's cool.
Yeah, you should listen to the interview that I did with you on the Orthodox engagement
podcast.
And even that was the tip of the item.
That's right.
Just a lot of weird chestnuts in there.
Yeah.
That doesn't seem to be.
who knows about by recently victorious blood feud against James Earl Joe.
I have won by virtue of being alive while he is dead.
Can confirm.
Video of me dancing on his grave incoming.
That's not a joke either.
I will film that.
I found many years ago that that would happen and it would.
But that video could be put behind some kind of wall if you want to do a fundraiser for
Ancient Faith.
I'm just starting out the fundraiser ideas tonight.
It's a CEO sit there.
Um, people don't need money to see me dance on this.
They absolutely will.
I think so.
I mean, uh, Anna Delvey, true name Anna Sorokina,
was on Dancing with the Stars.
So I mean, come on.
Yeah.
Right?
Okay.
So second half for realsies.
Um, so yeah.
So in the first half, I know it's a long time ago.
now that we did the first half of the show. But we set up sort of the relationship between
preceding Second Temple Judaism and Christianity as a paradigm of continuity with shifts, changes,
acculturations, etc. happening within. So let's just apply that as I promised many moons
ago we were going to to the relationship between
Christianity and a few different groups.
Okay, but so we'll start with Christianity and Nosticism.
Yeah, which is kind of a group of groups.
Yeah, which is a catch all category
that St. Euroneus invented as far as we can tell.
They didn't call themselves Nostics.
They called themselves various sects
like Sathians or Valentinians or what have you.
And he often added like the word so called.
Yeah
Great.
See, sarcasm is Christian, you guys.
Yes.
Just have to use it correctly.
So these two sets of communities, you've got Christian communities, you've got communities
that would fall into this Gnostic category.
They encounter each other.
We have literary artifacts of this encounter.
Right.
From both sides, actually.
And so we can see...
Right, how do they assess?
Are we the same the same thing? Are we the same group? Are we?
Doing the same thing is a continuity here or has there been a break?
Yeah, right as it been some kind of break where we're two separate
Two separate groups two different ways of life, right?
In modern terms two different religions though we talked about last time. Why that's not the best?
necessarily wait to look at it
So we get, using the criteria we set out before, right?
We get from, for example, St. Aaron As, one of our earliest statements regarding the New Testament canon,
based on precisely the issue of what scriptures are they using and what scriptures are we using.
So, first of all, it's out that they reject the Hebrew scriptures. They reject the Old Testament completely.
bunch of mercy nights.
right? So that's you know already but then even beyond that right?
St. Arneas points out go to all the cities where the apostles were they use
for gospels and only these four gospels these folks are reading these other
things right and those four gospels don't have authority in those
communities and then he looks at their relationship in terms of their way of
of life.
with the material creation.
Right, the God is created.
Yeah, this fundamental doctrinal issue.
Right.
And Christianity and preceedings like a temple Judaism,
especially with the fair sake variety,
embrace the physical creation as good,
believed in the bodily resurrection.
Right.
One of the things that makes these groups,
puts these groups into that category of Nostoc,
is that they reject that. They reject the goodness of creation.
they reject the
bodily resurrection. That's over the line. Yeah.
Christian groups, as we read in St.
Hernandez and others who are writing it's the Nesta groups,
have a continuity of authority structures, not just
parallel structures, right? We have parallel structures to
what the early church had, but there is a line of apostolic
succession that St.
Hernandez and other early fathers already the second
century point to going back to the Apostles.
Yeah, the authority is...
invested in the bishops not simply in charismatic figures who don't override the Episcopacy who
covered start their own sects like valentinus.
Yeah, right?
I mean, like, like, charismatic people can function as a corrective, right?
Like in a prophetic way, but they do not override.
Right.
Yeah.
And when a charismatic figure creates a community around themselves, that's a problem.
This is what we used to call it.
a heresy and now call it cult.
Yeah, exactly.
Like Montana's, where we the mountainous.
They importantly, very importantly, Nosticism introduces elements is formed.
What makes these Gnostic groups, Gnostic groups, right?
that they have brought together elements of Christ.
Christianity
And taking that and brought it into what is basically still paganism
Yeah, and if you read like if you really read the writers the Nostek writers
You you see what we're talking about like you actually take a look and see what they say
Yeah, it's all kinds of wacky weird super complicated
structures and cosmologies and yeah, yeah, right and so
So these things have been sort of pushed together.
If you cases, it's more vice versa.
It's they've taken these foreign pagan elements
and brought them into Christianity.
Usually it's the other, usually it's more pagan.
But there are some examples of the other.
But in either case, there is this artificiality
to narcissism.
Yes.
There is not this sort of history of development
of this being the religion of a particular people
who have practiced it and lived it.
It is there is some figure, some founding figure of this or that Nostex sect, who has done
the work of smushing these two things together.
Yeah, he'd be like, look.
Or interweaving these things.
You guys, I guess, some ideas.
Right, I mean, that's what he's, that, right.
They're like, I have an idea and I'm going to make it into something.
They're going to publicly preach it.
Rather.
Yeah.
Get people, get converts.
Right.
Artificial.
and that's why you have this whole panoply
of Gnostic's ex is that each one of the founders is sort of doing their math a little differently.
Right? As they construct this thing, but they're all sort of artificially constructed.
They don't grow out of the life of any people. I mean, it's even compared to paganism. Right? It's artificial. Yeah.
Yeah. Like paganism has a, has to use this word, but it's the word best where I can think of at the moment.
It has an authenticity to it that narcissism just...
is not. Right. Right. And so right there this artificial nature of it means that it's not the same
kind of thing as Christianity. Right. And not the same religion, not the same way of life.
It is still basically pagan. It's just a form of paganism that's been mutated
to look a little more like Christianity or incorporate some Christian elements. Yeah.
We see something very similar when we compare Christianity and Neoplatonism.
Now we're talking about more of the third century.
Neoplatonism, if you've heard of it, if you don't, we're talking about you've mostly
been taught a bunch of bunk-up.
Yeah, I mean, mostly it's...
I remember the presentations I heard about Neoplatonism when I was an undergraduate
You
back in the Jurassic period. And it was this idea that was just sort of refined version
of Platonism, which is not true, not historically actually true.
No, historically, Porphyry, who was Plutinus' forebearer philosophically, was a fierce
critic of Christianity. Because Christianity in the mid-3rd century was on the rise. And
He hated it.
right. Cated like platonic saginism despised it and platinous, particularly in his
any ads, but he is the founder of the School of Neoplatinism or he is
exhibit A at least. Then deliberately crafted a platonic pseudo Christianity. He
Deliberately.
borrowed Christian language and ideas, the ideas that he believed were appealing to people,
they were causing them to become Christians. I mean, he didn't care about slaves and women
becoming Christians, like people of the educated classes. Right? The ideas that were causing
people of the educated classes to become Christians and tried to incorporate them into
what was basically a platonic mold. Yeah, and we were in a sense to compete with Christianity.
Yeah, and this is why when you hear people start
talking about like Orthodox Christianity being Neoplatonic or Neoplatonic
influence on Christianity, you should kind of laugh at them because they don't
know what they're talking about. Because it's actually Christianity
influenced Platonism and that produced Neoplatonism. Yeah. The things you're
seeing are Christianity. Right. There is a similarity. Neoplatonism. Right. There's a
similarity but it went you know the
influence went in the other direct yes, yeah
There are similar arguments made by Daniel Boyar and by the way about middle Platonism and phylo Valegs Andrea
But you can look that up if you want it
So
But if we compare Christianity and Neoplatonism in the third century, right again
You find Christianity has the scriptures Neoplatonism rejects the whole idea of scriptures as such yeah
Yeah.
Right. Yeah. Um, the any, you know, platyne is, is not like their Bible. That's not how it works.
Plato's Republic is not their Bible. That's not how it works. Right. Um,
they, you know, Christianity, again, embraces material existence, the material creation calls it good. Obviously,
as any other form of Platonism, you know, Platonism rejects it. Right.
Christianity embraces, again, authority structures with the church.
There are no real authority structures in neoplatonism other than, again, charismatic individuals,
you know, the wise philosopher, the teacher, the charismatic teacher, right, like botanists
who gathers followers.
So, as we said, this is introducing Christian elements into Platonism that were foreign
elements.
And so, again, neoplatonism is artificial.
Yep.
Let's say religion that was crafted by people at a time we know when, right?
It's more like Scientology than it is like actual play-ness.
Right?
We just lost all our Scientologists listeners.
If we had any Scientologists listeners at this point, I would be flabbergasted.
The Thayton's got them.
Yeah, yeah.
All guests would be flabberged.
Right.
Like, I mean, explain this to me.
me right like spl-
There is no one in the world who enjoys being audited by like the IRX or an account me
Why would you call your religious ritual auditing? I know like that makes no sense. Okay
So great come on guys
um
I think if there's any one religious group that we can just go ahead and mercilessly mock on this show it probably the science
Scientology everyone else
We've got, you know, but I mean hey if you're a Scientologist and listening to this
So please call.
We would super love to hear from you.
Absolutely.
Donate money, because clearly you don't mind
going deeply into that for a religious reason.
Yeah.
So those are a couple of non-Christian groups
in the early church, right?
Yep.
But now we're going to let's apply this to a different group.
Yeah, a group that describes themselves as being Christians.
Let's apply this to
to Aryanism. Right. And not just Aryanism in the sense of like Aryus and what he was preaching,
not as like a set of ideas. But Aryanism, as Aryan Christian was practiced, there were
churches that were Aryanism. Actually communities, oh yeah, I mean there was big time, I'm
there doing missionary work up amongst the Goths. Right. The Goths were by a large western
Europe was mostly Aryan. Mostly in the build churches. They had liturgies. Aryan churches
in and around Consent's Noble.
Right. Yep.
Did you know, which was closed by the storyus?
Yeah. I say, did you know that St. John Chrysostom
in order to try to convert
Aryans in Constantinople who were largely Goths?
He started doing divine liturgy in some of his churches in Gothic
to try to win them over, which like could someone from the ancient world
please have preserved that text for us, but no, they did not.
I'm amazed they had to fake cobwebs in the...
white white made it. It was a very hot topic. There was a time. Yeah, there was no. Thank you.
So Richard Rollins laments the loss of that gothic divine liturgy. I think three times a day. Yeah.
He would. Yeah. Check's out. So yeah. So I'm an area of an
So, erinism and Christianity have...
Essentially the same scriptures, right?
Arianism and Christianity, right?
Now I'm talking about historical arianism now, right?
I know the Jehovah's Witnesses are Aryans,
but I'm not talking about the Jehovah's Witnesses right now.
I'm talking about the arian's with their arian churches.
Yeah, arian arian's.
In the fourth and fifth century.
Yeah.
Classic old school arian's.
Right.
They had basically the same way of life
the sense that they didn't differ on important points.
of morality, ethics, right, even worship structures from the Orthodox Church at the time, right?
I mean they even, I mean they used the Trinitarian invocations and things.
Oh yeah.
They met something different to them, but they used them, right?
Yeah.
And they had basically the same authority structures.
Yep.
Peace.
Priests, tickets. Priests, tickets.
Right. And, you know, take the second
Ecumenical Council out of the picture where they all got
Deposed, right? Those, those bishops could make a claim to
Apostolic succession, right? They had been consecrated by someone who was
consecrated by someone who was consecrated. Right. Yeah. Now they departed,
they departed from the faith, but they have that same structure there,
right? And so this is why.
I think there's a difference between Aryanism and Nosticism or Neoplatanism, for example,
in that Aryanism is not a different religion to use the modern terms, but is a false or
heretical Christianity.
Yeah.
And I mean, the early church fathers treated them that way.
Yes.
Like, the big question, of course, is if they decide to come into the church, how are
they received.
Areans are received by profession of faith only?
They don't even christmas. Yeah, it's a profession of thought. It's like Saint Basil. Yeah
This is a church father's and I think that's again. We're here trying to understand how the church understands things
This is why for example, I think Saint Basil would not baptize an Aryan who was returning to the church
But would definitely baptize the Neoplatanist or a Nostec. Yeah
no question
Right, yep, so there
there's something fundamentally different going on here.
Right?
Now that doesn't mean, that doesn't mean,
that doesn't mean that we're saying that
Aryanism or being an Aryan was not a problem.
Right.
Say it one more time, Uncle Steve.
Doesn't that?
Because having a false Christ means that you have a false
gospel, de facto.
Yeah.
If you're talking about a different Jesus,
you can't have the gospel.
You can't have your own...
personal Jesus. And that means Aryanism always lacked the power of Orthodox Christianity.
The power of God for salvation. So we are not saying we are just making a distinction that the
church has made between a false Christianity, a heretical Christianity and something that is not even
Christianity. Right. So they go work.
distorted versus something that is something else. So this gives the idea that
then those Aryan churches, or if you want to talk about them collectively, do
I talk about the Aryan church? That's kind of an anachronism because they didn't
really have any overarching structures. They didn't really build them the way the
orthodox church data the sense that there weren't sort of like
area
patriarchs, you know, there was a patriarch of the Visigoths and the right leg.
But if we want to talk about collectively as the area church, that would be a heretical
body.
Right.
And if you're part of a heretical body, that's not great.
That's not a great place to be.
Yeah, don't do it, you guys.
Yeah.
Try to avoid it.
If you're part of what now leave, enjoy the Orthodox Church.
Oh.
So, be part of a radical body, right?
Is gonna limit, is gonna limit
what you're able to do in terms of coming to know God.
Right, because-
For your perspective.
Right, because if you have a false idea of someone,
a false understanding of who that person is,
which frankly, most radical bodies,
that's the big question, right, is who is Jesus
and they get it wrong.
If you have a false idea of who someone is,
then you're going to
relate to them in a way that is distorted.
No matter who it is, Christ or anybody,
if you have radically wrong ideas about a person,
it's gonna affect the way that you relate to that person.
Right, so it's gonna be taught things that aren't true.
Yeah, that's not gonna be helpful to you.
Yeah, so it's, I mean, like,
heresy has a very practical effect.
Yeah, but at the same time, we maintain,
that you being part of a heretical body
doesn't limit what Christ can do.
He's God.
Right.
Let's talk about that for a second in...
Yeah, nothing can limit God.
But let's talk about for a second in the case of, you know,
your peasant, your peasant to Visigoth, right?
Whose king has converted to Christianity of the Aryan type.
Yes.
And therefore, you go to the Christian church in your village,
which happens to be Aryan, because you're a Visigoth,
and you don't have the options.
Okay, like there's only...
on church, that's the only Christian church, okay?
It is not impossible for Christ to save that peasant
just because he's going to a heretical church.
And Algust Overseer to say,
it's definitely better that that Visigoth,
and I have to say by the way,
I first learned about Visigoths and Austrogoths
from asterisk synoplics comics.
Yeah.
That my father brought home from his travels in the Navy.
It is better for that Visigoth to be...
an Aryan Christian, then it was for him to have been sacrificing to Thor.
That is, it is better, you guys.
It is better.
It's not ideal, but it's definitely better.
Right, but being part of that heretical body is in some ways not going to help him.
as he seeks to work out his salvation.
Right? It would be better for him
where he in an Orthodox church
that knows the true Christ and is preaching the true Christ.
Oh, wow. We just got to note.
I think we have a first, at least that I'm aware of,
our first live listener tuning in from India.
Oh. So, hello India.
Yes. We're glad to have you tuning in.
So...
Exhibit A of this who we can point to in church tradition is of course St. Isaac the Syrian or St. Isaac of Nineveh
Right who
Connotically belongs as far as we know and I know there's some quibbling over this
But as far as we know
Connotically belongs to the Assyrian Church of the East commonly known as the historians
Right we're not saying that St. Isaac was an historian. No
We're saying he was due to where he lived and when he lived
left, right.
a member of a heretical body. Right? Right? He's part of her heretical body. And the church has
recognized him. He didn't have a lot of choices. As a saint. Right? But he became a saint
to the work of Christ and his cooperation with that work because him being part of that heretical
body didn't stop Christ from saving him. Right? Now I would not recommend anyone going join the
the Church of the East if they want to become a saint.
But we have to record with the reality of world history.
Yeah.
Right.
And God did not cause people to be born in places, in centuries, where he was automatically
damning them to hell.
That's been declared a heresy by the church, Second Council of Orange.
It always cracks me up with Calvinists when Calvinists cite the second council of orange
about quote unquote semi-plegianism when it condemns reprobation as a heresy.
But basically precludes Calvinism.
But that reprobation is a heresy.
And saying that God had someone be born in Mesoamerica in the 12th century where there
there was no knowledge of Christianity, and that means they went to hell.
for eternity is
Reprobation yeah, you are being a Calvinist
Even if you don't think you're for yourself as one or what maybe if you think that you are and if there's one thing
You should come away from Laura Spirits podcast with kids. It's it's don't be a Calvin. Don't do a Calvinism
Not even once not even once
See the thing is I can pick on the Calvinist because I know they can take it
Right like they say they can no no they can
again, they get trusted.
Because I think a Calvinist likes more
than a good theological route.
Absolutely.
In the case.
So, especially if there's some beers involved.
So, yeah, so that being the case, right,
if that's a heresy, then what has to be true
in the positive sense of the church's teaching
is that it is possible for anyone
who has ever lived
at any time in any place to find salvation.
Right, and that's because,
and I think this is a really important concept first to grasp.
If you do something good, it is good.
If you're doing something good,
I mean, it seems weird to say that, right?
But there's a whole theological world out there
that says that unless you check off certain boxes,
everything you do is other garbage.
Like that is totally a thing in certain theological,
that's totally a thing, right?
They'll say, oh, your righteousness is filthy rags. That's not what that means. But
You know a good act is a good act and every good act is faithfulness to God and faithfulness to God is cooperating with divine grace
right
And and I mean to me one of the prime exhibits of this is
in the book of Jonah
Right Jonah goes to Nineveh of course having had his arm twisted a lot
but he goes
sin and of a and he doesn't even say you guys if you don't repent you know bad things are going to happen
He just says in three days, Ninova will be overthrown like he's just it's just all doom and gloom and and what do the Ninovites do
They repent and sack cloth and ashes right
Interesting interesting detail though were never told and history bears out
That they did not convert from paganism
to become worshipers of Yahweh the God.
out of Israel. Didn't happen. They continue to be demon worshipping pagans. And yet, God not only
spares their city because they repented, but then Christ Himself in the Gospels, in both Matthew and
Luke, holds them up as an example of repentance. He says, and it's word for word, by the way, in both
these hospitals. The men of Nineveh will rise up at the judgment with this
and condemn it for they repent to the preaching of Jonah and behold something greater than Jonah's here.
So it's an interesting point.
Here's a bunch of demon worshipping penguins and there's God in the flesh honoring their repentance and holding them up as an example.
Yeah. Yeah. As we said last time, there is some way that at least some hunter-gatherers found salvation.
Yeah.
Yeah, being faithful.
the revelation that God had given to them.
And the grace of God in the world, which was a tiny, tiny, tiny drip compared to the
revelation we've been given.
But that just means we're held more accountable.
Yep.
Right.
But this is how we're told, guys, get judges the world.
And you can say Paul says this in Romans 1 and Romans 2 and Romans 10.
This is Part and Parcel, Acts 17.
This is part parcel of what the New Testament teaches regarding how salvation works.
Right. And they're not being a mecha. So salvation is available to every was available to every person who has ever lived that doesn't mean they all received it. Yeah.
And it doesn't mean that the exact shape of what that faithfulness was was the same. Yeah. Depending on more or less it been revealed, but it was possible. And it doesn't possible. Yeah.
or medieval Roman Catholics in France.
It was possible, it's possible for evangelical Protestants
to the United States.
it's possible it was possible for uh
Chinese people in the 8th century BC
Is it possible for Huguenots though?
It was possible. It was possible.
They destroyed the relics of St.
your day as I know Huguenots and Henry VIII man.
Yeah, but so all this is to say but that fact the fact that God can still save people who are members of heretical bodies is not
Saying that does not say anything positive about the heretical body itself right
right
Right it does not say anything about the heretical body itself
The only positive you could say about the heretical body itself is that
that problem if it's a heretical body,
meaning it is in some way a deformed version of Christianity.
There's some Christianity still there.
Maybe a lot.
Maybe only a little.
But there's some Christianity still there.
And so that Christianity that is still there will be an aid
to those within that body who are seeking salvation.
Yeah.
Right.
And there I'm kind of paraphrasing Archbishop of Verky.
But yeah.
And an interesting note here,
an interesting note here
uh...
a lot of people don't know historically what it was that converted the gods
right because that of at a for a long time the gods outnumbered
orthodox christians like saint amber is a cathedral was surrounded
at several points about the carbies who are all areas
what transformed it was not some kind of mission endeavor or public debates
on theology or any of that
with St. Martin of Tours.
The St. Martin of Tours was a wonder worker in his life, and God continued to work miracles
through his relics after St. Martin's death.
And so the shrine where his relics were became a place of pilgrimage and veneration for the
Goths, even though they were Aryans.
And so when I said that the heretical bodies and stuff sort of lack the power in a certain
way that the church has...
This is what I mean.
Right.
And the Goth sought and it led to mass conversions
to the faith of Saint Mark.
Yeah.
I think his relics are still,
I think they are still available in tours.
I've heard of people that have venerated them there.
Yeah.
There's some here in Louisiana.
Oh, hey.
Hey.
I'm have to make a book of Mitch Louisiana.
Only to go to a crawfish boil.
Yeah.
All right, on a fast day, you can go.
That's right, man.
All right, well, that wraps up the second half
of this 100th episode of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Think of how many hundreds, literally now,
hundreds of hours.
Y'all have been listening to us go on and on.
On two ages of ages.
How about that?
All right, we're gonna go ahead and take our second
and final break, and when we get back,
we're gonna listen to another clip,
and we're gonna talk to some of y'all.
So.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your
calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
You've probably heard of St. Rafael Halloweeny, St. Alexander Hodevitsky, liturgical translator
is a bell hap-good and other rights
men and women who made their mark on the early development of orthodoxy in America.
But what about the notorious, itinerant Bulgarian monk, or Father Rafael Morgan, the first
Black Orthodox priest in America?
Or Vera Johnston, who served the Orthodox Church without renouncing her theosophist
roots?
There are stories in many others, some edifying, some appalling, all entertaining, make up
the lost histories of the early decades of Orthodox Christianity.
in the continental United States.
Lost histories, the good, the bad, and the strange
in early American Orthodoxy by Matthew Naney.
Out now at store.enginefaith.com.
Again, that is store.enginefaith.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now.
855-237-2346. That's 855-AF radio.
Welcome back. It's the thousandth episode of The Lord of Spheres. It feels like that's
in time. I mean, 10,000s times, 10,000s of episodes. That's right. I feel like we could
be a Johnny Cash song. Yeah. One of my favorite Johnny Cash songs is when the man comes around.
You know that one?
Yes, that's a that's a great song
How long will you kick against the prick? I know I know man Johnny Cash
Right, we have actually decided to call a little bit of an audible on this
Millionsth episode of the Lord of Spheres podcast and
We're going to play the third half clip
for everybody and
And then we are simply going to spend
some amount of time talking to y'all.
So just get your calls on people.
And don't worry though.
Yeah, yeah, we're not talking.
We're gonna talk about the third half.
This'll be a future episode, yeah, yeah.
We'll be part three in our next episode.
So we'll come back to it.
But the amount of material we had to go through
was unless we wanted to make this the 24 hour marathon
was not going to happen.
Yes.
And this is an anniversary episode.
Exactly.
We're having...
fun. Exactly. Exactly. Exactly. So you will not miss out on anything. Yeah. Call
everybody. And if you get like a busy signal or whatever, it just means that the lines are jammed.
But just keep calling. Just keep calling. You know, just like remember Cameron and one of those
and one of the best movies ever made. He kept saying he'll keep calling me. He'll keep calling me.
No, Rooney!
See, if you just drop that reference...
I would have thought you were making a totally out of character joy division reference.
No, no, no.
I'm near Chicago, you know?
So obviously I have to think about one of the greatest Chicago films of all time.
But we were also talking about Goths.
That weep for the future.
Yes.
So, yeah, let's go ahead and play clip number three there, Trudy.
And then we'll start talking to some people.
Hard to understand.
There we go.
So that's why you would have.
those chambers underneath the Sphinx, right?
What's now the Sphinx?
Oh.
And the position, right?
People have noted, of course, that when you look at
the Great Pyramid and the Row Pyramids, how this lines up
astrologically with the constellations
directly above during certain times of years.
So those times of year are festival periods,
but more importantly, within the...
Egyptian cosmology, you have this mirroring of the structures and order on earth are mirrored
in the heavens and vice versa.
Oh, well, it's just like it says in the Psalms or in our father on earth as it is in heaven.
Right.
So this is extended with the idea, of course, that within the Egyptian cosmology
you have kind of ongoing constant battle in heaven, right?
You have Ray and a poffis, right?
Battling each other every night, right?
And so the calamities in chaos on Earth
is mirroring this kind of calamity in chaos in heaven.
Yeah, and there's this, and I was gonna say there's obviously a fatalism attached to that,
which is like the gods are gonna do what they're gonna do,
to do and we're kind of subject to that.
Right, it's that it's going to be mirrored.
So the astrology can kind of give you a heads up, right?
But it's not like you can change anything.
Yeah, yeah.
Right.
So then how would an ancient Egyptian pagan understand?
I mean, obviously there's just be royals making
this decisions, but the important people deciding,
okay, we're going to build this monument
in order to participate.
I mean, couldn't you have said, you know, well,
I
I don't want to participate in that.
Forget that.
I'm not going to build this monument that astrologically aligns with all the rest.
Well, that would fundamentally call into question for the Pharaoh to do that.
We call into question his own identity, which of course he was projecting as divine.
Yeah, because he's the son of Ray or probably or maybe some other one of the chorus.
Yeah, yeah, so it's sort of his duty.
what makes in the Pharaoh is the fact that he is doing this, that he is doing this kind
of mirroring.
And so there's continuities and discontinuities between that and the idea of imaging.
Yeah.
That's crazy.
I mean, as a relatively obscure pop culture reference, the thing that suddenly occurs
to me is, did you ever play the game Age of Mythology?
Yes.
but it was a long time ago.
Yeah, yeah.
Yeah, it's one of those, what they call RTS, real-time strategy.
And you can play as the Greeks, you can play as the Norris, you can play as the Egyptians.
That's in the original version and they add some other civilizations, I think later.
And you have to accumulate, I can't remember what they call it.
Anyways, it's represented by a little lightning symbol.
And you have to accumulate that as one of the sort of currencies you can spend on units.
And...
With the Greeks, you have to put people worshipping at a temple in order to get that.
With the Norse, it's actually fighting.
Fighting gets you more of that.
But with the Egyptians, it's monuments.
And the bigger the monuments you build, the more that's generated.
And of course, the more that you have, the more that's generated as a result.
And obviously, it's a very just reductionist gamified approach to this kind of thing.
But, you know, it's not entirely dissimilar from what you just described.
with a sense that, okay, if you build,
if you're the Pharaoh and you build the Sphinx,
this confirms that you're the Pharaoh.
It, you know, and then confirming you're the Pharaoh
gains the obedience and favor of your people,
like everybody's kind of doing what they're supposed to do.
And so therefore, Egyptian society works the way
that it is supposed to work just as predictable
and beneficial as the flooding of the Nile.
Right.
Avis
established justice. Yeah. And yeah, and yeah, that is sort of the video game version of
Sid Meyer combined with Sid Roth.
So did I ever tell you about the time that I almost extinguished the eternal flame?
You have, but I don't think you've said this on the air here live.
Okay, yeah, maybe this is the time for the world to know. So obviously, we're talking about
about Egyptians so it may be think of the Bengals as one does.
And yes, so back in.
1997 when I was still a stagehand, the initial run of Lilith Fair, which that's a wonderful
Lord of Spirits reference right there, although they mean something very different by it.
But they just sort of run a Lilith Fair, came to the big arena where I often worked during
the summer doing concerts.
And 1997 actually did a whole pile of concerts.
Like it was the last year of the first run of Lala Paloza, it was the
first year of Lilith Fair.
And so, you know, so Lilith Fair, of course,
was for all of you young people out there.
It was a tour of female artists
that were a big deal in the mid 1990s.
And even some that had been a big deal
for much longer than that.
Among whom, obviously, is Susanna Hobs.
I can remember is it Hobs or Hobs?
It's Hobs.
So yeah, the lead singer of the bangles.
And so she was backstage.
And I can't remember what she was doing, but she was backstage and she was kind of near
the loading dog.
And I was going from point A to point B. I don't remember what it is that I was tasked with
doing, but I remember that I had to get there and make it happen quickly.
Which, you know, doing production work, doing theater, doing concerts occasionally, stage
ends have to move fast.
And so I was going somewhere very quickly.
And at the last second, I kind of moved out of the way because she was there.
And the thing is that she is not tall,
not even a little bit, like she's not even average.
I don't know where exact type,
but she is a small person.
She is we.
Exactly.
And unlike we.
And so, but I realized as I turned around,
like if I had not moved out of the way,
cause I was just sort of barreling along,
I would have knocked her down,
like 10, 15 feet or whatever.
was into the loading dock.
And I mean, how could I have explained to my friends
and family later on that I was the one
who had extinguished the eternal flame?
Like, I could have never, ever, ever lived that down.
So yeah, so that's what makes me think.
You know, now that you've told that story live on the air,
now people are gonna wanna know how I got Ben from Stonehenge.
Yeah.
Well.
Someday we'll tell that story.
Someday, someday, maybe that'll happen.
Alright, one of my favorite good times indeed.
Alright, we're just going to open up the lines.
So I'm sure we've got some collars there.
Do we have collars I assume, Trudy?
Yes, yes.
Trudy the tank, Richter everybody.
Manning the tank.
See, I'm going to say this at least ten times the emphasis that everybody in the collars are the tank.
You meet Trudy.
M1 Abrams.
Oh yeah.
Yeah, yeah, no, I think she got a suba word talking military tank we could be fish tank
No, I mean no like D&D tank
Oh, okay. Yeah, like could be you know world-world aircraft tank totally. Yeah. Yeah propane tank
Exactly exactly exactly
Exactly true
so all right
Hello caller welcome to Laura's spirit's podcast
Hello my own you're on what's your name?
Hi my name is
will from Texas. Welcome will from Texas. What part of Texas you in?
Car what you say what part they cut out a little bit. Yeah what part?
Uh, all like five minutes from Oklahoma. Pretty. Oh okay. I'm told that Oklahoma is Texas's hat.
I've been told that. Is that true? Yeah. Okay. I guess I lived in Oklahoma and we always call
their self-exit hats. No one does that actually never that before.
Oh, people fire at you.
It was, it was Richard Rohan who said that to me that, uh, that Oklahoma's Texas has had.
So what's on your mind, Will from Texas, almost Oklahoma?
Yeah, I'm kidding.
Oh, my question is about, uh, so on Acts 22, Paul,
he's telling this and he's telling this story about how he's in the temple in
Jerusalem he has a little translike and that is what is that is that it well I've
never been anybody talk about I've seen visions you know but he specifically
says trans like you cutting it out there but I think we got the gist he's asking
about, we'll see Paul in a trance.
Is that just a...
Translation wackiness, follow. Yeah, are we cutting out?
A little bit, but I think we got the idea you're asking like is he in a trans and what does that mean? Is that what you're saying?
Yeah, what does that mean? Is it different from a vision? Is it a specific kind of praying? What's going on?
Yeah, so what's what's being
translated there is that he was in sort of an ecstatic state. He was an ecstasy
meaning he was sort of having a
visionary experience. And this is his
version story, which we know St. Paul had more than once. It happened on the road to Damascus.
It happened. He describes it happening in 1 Corinthians. This is something that St. Paul
had visions while he was in prayer at certain times. And Christ appeared to him multiple
times in person, not just on the road to Damascus, but a couple of other times in the book of
facts. So yeah.
This is something that happened to St. Paul, but it's not like a reflection of some kind of technique of prayer or something that like we could use or
Someone could use don't don't tell certain evangelicals about this because they'll write a book and claim you could do it too
Don't try this at home not all evangelicals. I said certain even certain. Yeah
Yeah, there's certain ones. Yeah, not the ones I not the ones I grew up with they don't do this
not the better sort
Yeah. It's like a special revelation.
It's like repinting, really, really meditate,
just like a special rebel.
Yeah, it's, he kind of goes into an ecstasy.
But it's not like a thing you can schedule on Sunday morning.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah. So, all right.
that's helpful will from Texas on
Oklahoma. Yeah, I appreciate it guys. Great. Thanks for calling. Okay. We're gonna go ahead
take another caller. Welcome caller. The Lord of Spirits podcast are one hundredth in a one hundredth
episode fourth anniversary. Extravapalooza. Ganza. Hello, my own. You are on. What's your name?
I'm my name's Timothy. I'm Georgia. I'm getting hit by that hurricane right now. Oh, man, you okay?
by the way. You're right. Yeah, yeah, I'm up. Yeah, I'm up in North Georgia, but we're
bad winds and it's a pray for us up here. Yeah. Too bad you don't have that one to say
free Paris. I was gonna say it's too bad you don't have Pat Robertson to like turn it
away. Okay, I get in trouble around here if I say that. This is our spirits with your
Closed doors closed, the windows drawn.
Yeah.
Lighted around.
That's right, exactly.
Ain't.
should be the radio after dark.
So my question, and I'm running into this constantly,
and I call all the few weeks back
and I asked the question about the onion of pride.
But it's about the translations of words
and how they're used today in normal language
versus how they were used and have been translated as such.
So for example, we're doing my work recently
you a study of the song and
started someone this week and you know the first the first of the first someone
blessed is the man who walks in the not in the council of the ungodly now that's
my that is my orthodox study Bible but my ancient faith Salthor said blessed is
the man who walks not in the council of the wicked so you know for me growing
out in the south wicked had a very definite definition and so just reading it
this way without having my study Bible.
as well, which is the reason I'm even bringing this up is because our pre-stated of the Bible
and I was like, well, that's what my book says.
So I looked it up.
How does a layman, how does someone who's just trying to educate themselves, not fall into
this trap where this word wicked obviously doesn't mean wicked as in the evil, like wicked
which is a West type of situation, right?
It means other than God, not God's ways, ungodly.
when you, you know, and I guess we can be taken that way as well, but
It's just in laymen's for a layman that's not studied any kind of translations or any of that.
It can get a little confusing.
It makes sense.
Yeah.
I mean, there's a bunch of different ways to translate.
I mean, the number one, there's the Hebrew, which Father Stevens, the Hebrew scholar.
The Greek word that's in the Septuagin is asevon, which literally means empires.
Isn't that right?
Like, empires?
I think that sounds right.
Yeah.
I'm godly
mean ungodly would be a because
you could translate
so is he is godly
yeah
yeah and then that the he brew is more common
russia i don't know what that means it i mean that gets translated to godly
uh... right but that could be
yet ratio that's i mean that could be evil
or way that's why it's probably translated wicked
yeah
and you see my problem right if you guys are debating this one word how
someone who has no education in this.
like figure it out and understand what demeaning of it with without having to call my priest
every ten seconds when running to the word I want to make sure I'm reading it the right way.
You're poor priest.
Well I mean I think okay but let's think about this right. I mean number one you should talk
to your priest about how you read the Bible. Obviously not every five seconds.
Yeah, you know, I just got to verse two father
Yeah.
Maybe like, look, I'm trying to have dinner so could you call maybe tomorrow or yeah, but
I mean, the point being, right, that when we read the scriptures, it is okay to read
the scriptures and not have a conversation about every single verse.
That's okay.
It's okay.
But what you shouldn't do is decide that you know exactly what it means and then sort
get puffed up and an absolute ties your meaning and arguing
with people about it.
And realize that in some cases,
multiple translations of a single word
can give you different aspects
of what's going on in the scriptures.
Like so like the Hebrew original,
is an orthodox Bible verse,
and the Greek translation is an orthodox Bible verse,
and the slow-
Translation is an orthodox Bible verse and English translations can be orthodox and they may all say slightly different things and that's okay and they all function within the church
To do what it needs that needs to be done
Right, so it's it's really about the whole matrix within which we receive the scriptures and
It's not only about an isolated
solitary experience of reading the Bible.
When you read the Bible as an Orthodox Christian, you read it as an Orthodox Christian with the
Orthodox Church, which means that not only do you bring to it your experience of having
been in church, your experience of having been taught by your priests and by other teachers,
your experience of having been formed by the church services, your experience of having
read the lives of the saints and whatever else, but also that you are willing to be corrected
if you're reading something wrong.
You know?
So yeah, I mean ungodly and wicked, like to me, really, these are two words that can kind of point to the same direction. Now in English, wicked lands differently than ungodly.
For sure. Right. There's something about that word wicked.
But, clearly to be ungodly is not good either.
So I think they just sort of land a little bit differently for an English speaker.
It is my sense of it.
So I would say both of these spheres, I don't want to take away a horrible mis-translation
because I ascribe a definition to a word that isn't intended based on the translation
from the original text or even the Greek text.
Yeah.
I mean some of it is a matter of different translations come from different periods of
English, right?
So like in interestingly enough, that Hebrew word, like the King James, for instance, translates
that Hebrew word there as ungodly, but translates that exact same Hebrew word elsewhere as wicked
in the same translation, produced at the same time. Right? So it's okay. It's okay. It's gonna be okay.
Yeah, I mean it's not it's not a case where the two translations mean total
opposite things. Obviously. And there aren't any examples of that that I know of in reputable English
translations. Now if you start getting into like the New World translation with Joe
as witnesses, the other's the passion translation or the message. King James the edited version of
the King James Bible, the Mormon, sometimes give out now you're in different territory. Oh yeah.
Yeah.
Um, but I think it's just a good idea to not only read one translation.
Just read things like you did, right?
Comparing your ancient face, altered your Orthodox study Bible, right?
And generally, if you compare a couple translations, you can kind of by reading a couple different
translate, get the gist of what's going on, right?
Without putting too much weight on one particular English word choice.
And reading a whole lot into that English word, right?
If you've got a couple of different English words, you could probably, from the two of them,
figure out, okay.
Right?
This is...
talking about people who are doing the wrong thing, right?
People who are living their life in a sinful, ungodly, wicked way, right?
And from those two translations, you get the gist, right?
And you don't.
You know, I don't know if I've mentioned this on the air, but I once heard,
and I categorized this as the worst sermon I ever heard.
I heard a guy who was preaching verse by verse through the New Testament.
So he was preaching, just read a verse, preach a whole sermon on that verse, right?
He read the first verse of the parable of the Good Samaritan, which is a certain man went down to Jericho and
Immediately launched into brethren. We must be certain in our faith
It was real
But if you have a couple of different translations, you're not gonna fall into that kind of trap
Right, you're not gonna, because you're gonna see.
for English words that could be the same general idea, right?
Well, that's actually, thank you for suggesting that I read out of multiple sources because I
kind of kind of gravitate towards my softer for the songs, right?
Just because it's, I saw it's there where I have to look for it in my Orthodox study
Bible because it's kind of in the middle there so.
But yeah, I guess I need to be more aware of that and I really appreciate you guys directing
me that direct push me.
direction. You're welcome. Thanks very much for calling. Thanks for listening.
All right. Who's next, Judy? Bring him in. We don't know who's that. Yeah, we know. That's right.
We don't know because these are unscreened everybody. This is the first time we've done this.
anniversary. Yeah, but I mean, you know, but, but, but, but, Judy is ready. Just like,
hit the big red button to cut people off if they get out of hand. Oh, the dump button. That's
That's right.
I'm surprised you just used that on me all the time.
I've told her to a couple times, if whatever reason.
Yes.
Anyway, welcome color to the Lord of Spheres podcast.
It's our 100th episode.
Hello?
Yeah, hello.
Oh, hi.
Who said who's next?
I wanted to say my name is Bill Goldberg.
But no, this is Dino from Chicago.
All right, Dino of Chicago.
Welcome to Lord of Spheres podcast.
I think I see your reference for the record.
Yeah.
Okay.
I might, so the question is turning the heroin of hell because, you know, Mel Gibson just
recently announced he's going to do the sequel to the Passion of the Christ and to the Resurrection
and that's naturally exactly where my mind went because most people think, well, obviously
like what happens later.
So I get all excited.
and talk and to many Catholic friends,
some of them PhD, CCD, and I-
I was talking about what they call the heroin of hell,
what they call the heroin of Hades.
They had no idea what I was talking about.
So I was completely dumbfounded,
and I would explain to them what we learned
from all these Saturday and a little bit
of the pastoral sermon and the icons.
And then they come to me and like,
well, we're just scriptural support for this
and that's where I was lost.
Wait, Robert and I have to go through that?
That's what they told me.
Where were your t-
What?
the Bible on catacas. Absolutely. They teach CCD. Well, I mean, I mean, not every catacas
in Sunday school teacher in the Orthodox Church is up to speed on all they should be up
to speed on. I'm just going to put that out there. Right. And I saw the embarrassment.
I was in company with the evangelical Protestants when I were talking about this because, you
know, I was expecting that from them, but, you know, from, you know, because I asked them,
Well, what do you guys think happened in three days?
And they're like,
you just put the send in the hell and he just hung out like what he did.
So I, but then you know it got more serious and it was like okay, well where is this
in, is it just tradition or is this kind of written in prophecy or what?
Because I was at a loss as to what I could explain what our teaching was and
And to them they just thought I was just making it up.
Which, you know,
with my personality, they might have thought that I was,
because sometimes I'll say,
because I'm Greek or that we just reinvented everything
anyway, because we're Greek.
So here's my Greek and Greeks invented everything paradox.
I just have to, since I'm talking to an actual Greek
and a Chicago Greek, right?
Are you from Chicago?
Yeah, yeah, from Chicago.
So you are your own ethnicity of Greek, okay?
And you know what I mean, right?
Chicago Greeks are their own kind of Greek, right?
So if it is the case, if it is the case.
Greeks invented everything then they would have to have invented being Greek and
So then how does that happen since they weren't Greek yet and Greeks invented everything
Just I'm just throwing that out there figure that one out for me
What I'd say is
My Spark remark back will Greek this really is an excellent and we call ourselves aliens
Beware of denance carrying
exonems. Alright. Okay. Okay. So yeah, there is stuff in the scripture that points to the
harrowing of Hades or Hell. You know, Psalm 24 for instance, you know, lift up your gates
so you princes be lifted up, you everlasting gates in the king of glory, Sri Lentur, and who
is the King of glory, the Lord's strong and mighty, the Lord mighty and war.
Right? So that has been understood by the church as about Christ coming in and
busting up the dark Lord's hood. So there's that. And then there's of course
also the references to the Holy One not seeing corruption in the grave. But like
the real fleshing out of this is not explicit in the scripture. You get the
dramatization that's in
what's called the gospel of Nicodemus or the Acts of Pontius Pilate, which is my favorite iteration of that.
And you know there's a lot of the liturgical material, but I mean Roman Catholic Catechists you guys
just like, come on, know your own tradition.
Hello.
What is it?
It's different than what we have or is it?
You know?
because I'm always envision more of like a battle.
And, you know, maybe, and from an artistic perspective,
I'm thinking there's a lot of imagination
that your imagination can go wild,
because you might not be bounded by scripture,
but, you know, what are the minimum kind of elements
that Mill Gibson might have?
Because, you know, my, I'm really excited about this.
I don't know, Mill Gibson, okay.
I mean, I appreciate many things that Mill Gibson has made,
for sure.
Absolutely.
Right mostly involving Danny Glover.
It's getting too old for anyway.
He is.
I know. I know.
But I mean God bless him. He is a hyper set of a contest.
Catholic dude. So I mean who knows exactly what it is he's going to do.
But no, I think that my understanding and I'm not Roman Catholics,
so I can't speak for them, but this is my impression.
My impression is that their tradition about this is mostly basically the same thing as ours.
At least, yeah, sort of, but like their art, for instance, never depicts like a pitched battle.
It does depict Jesus flattening Satan with the gates of Hades. It does, right?
One of my favorites is the painting by Hirannama's Bosch, where you see this really dark,
evil hellish place and then there's this
and then the door is opening up and he's being pushed in by Christ with a cross like a big pole and there's light flooding and you know and you get like you almost think that the caption is like he's coming in you know
but but yeah it's not all together that different from what we believe i'm kind of shocked i described it as like a special forces mission you know where you know christ's trick tady to get kind of let him into the door like almost like a trojan horse type of thing and
Oh, totally, that's a patristic image.
is that Dick Jaggers has. Yeah, Chris, you know, the sort of hell took a body and met God. Surprise. Right. Yeah. Yeah.
I know that's, I actually read them the pastoral sermon and they all thought it was awesome. It's an okay, come to North. It is awesome.
Yeah. It's actually in the Catechus with the Catholic Church. It's yeah. They call it the census added pharaohs. That's the Latin name for it. Yeah.
you know, Latin their language.
But yeah, and so...
You don't speak a lot differently.
Something we have to do.
So, let me have some remedy.
Or tell them to go read Thomas Aquinas
about the limbo of the fathers.
Oh.
Right.
There's like this sort of,
they've developed the Abraham Spusa idea
or like the caves and hideies
in the book of Enoch or that kind of thing
into this idea that limbo's
are sort of pockets of hell
that aren't as bad as the rest of hell.
Basically, it's the short version
in Latin Christianity.
and
So there's a limbo of unbaptized infants and there's a limbo of the fathers which is now
empty.
The limbo of the fathers is where all those folks from the Old Testament went who were
going to be saved.
Yeah, I heard a limbo.
Yeah, that Jesus went to the limbo of the fathers and emptied it out.
Yeah.
Okay.
Which is not entirely dissimilar from what is in our tradition, but obviously the language
is different and the fact that they have this
other category of a limbo or different kinds of limbo's that's not what we do but so but those
and then you know modern Catholics will say well the limbo things a figure of speech or whatever
yeah they've kind of disavowed all in art it like daily jello to a wall but that's it retomis
a coin is that's what you get right like yeah but it is clearly taught in scripture in first
speeder, but you have to make... there's an extended argument to show somebody how it's
taught. They get into the group.
and some of St. Peter's Greek word choices and stuff.
Right, like to prove that that's what it's talking about.
But you can't prove it.
It's just complicated.
Yeah.
Does that help?
I just tell them what it says.
You know, and then they'll believe me.
There you go.
Yeah.
Like, look, I'm Greek, okay.
I'm reading the Bible as my language.
How it goes?
Let's just tell it is, that's the Chicago way.
No, the Chicago way is if they bring a knife,
you bring a gun.
They put one of yours in the hospital. You put one of theirs in the morgue. That's right. That's yeah
And before you said who's next I was gonna I was gonna introduce myself as Abe Roman
Nice. Yes. Thank you
The sausage king of Chicago. Good night. Thank you for calling. Dina. Okay. Welcome next caller to the Laura Spears podcast
Welcome welcome. It's you
Hello!
Yeah hello!
Oh, live radio everybody.
Oh, hi.
Yeah.
This is a Hunter.
I'm a Catholic in Texas.
And oh, do you have something to say about Dino?
Is this a sad in Pharaoh?
Do you know about this?
I was actually kind of reading up on it,
as you all are talking about it.
So, wait, this is a thing?
Yeah, I've actually really come to appreciate
Psalm 24, thanks in large parts of your show.
Thank God.
I have the all to thank for that.
God.
But yeah, I was actually kind of wondering in a recent show, one of y'all kind of mentioned
in passing the Catholic doctrine of being like in a state of grace, and that's kind of
how we're brought up that.
Either you're in or you're out.
did we lose him? Did you hang up on him, Trudy?
He fell out of the state of R-
great. He's now lost to us. Oh, I know what happened. All I just I just saw
Trinity pushing buttons and then suddenly he's highly a tube sense of irony.
I know. It's a great boom. All right. When I see if we could try to get him back
but meanwhile we'll talk to whoever the next person is. So hello next
Collar you've you've you've successfully connected Lorda Spears podcast.
Welcome.
Twinsheaks actually question.
Oh, yes.
I'm going home now.
I was at a retreat last week and somebody came up and said they had a question for me that
they did want to call it about because it was about they said do you have a theory about
Lost Highway, the David Lynch movie.
And I was like of course I have a theory about Lost Highway.
But anyway, Twin Peaks question.
Alright, we'll take the Q&A piece question. I think we have hunter was his name.
I think we haven't done.
Jewels live with you.
Yeah.
So anyway.
So spoiler for anyone who hasn't seen Twin Peaks, but used to part whenever a Josie Packard
dies as like the little dancing man or does she, does she die?
Well, she does, that's a part of the question.
That is a part of the question.
Okay.
So we have the little dancing man from the other place who's dancing over, but then before
that Yolson Bob who appears.
like Taunt Cooper. He's a little dancing man. He appears also over the bed. He does a little jig.
And then you see Josie's face kind of getting like mangled into this wooden knob.
And he's contorted. What exactly is going on? Because my knowledge of Tibetan Buddhism and
street lights and our Syrian legends, you know, I'm coming up short here, Father.
I have to say before you answer father Stephen. I wish you could see the look on
in this face right now. Yes, so you can imagine.
So you have to remember here is that everything in the great Northern, all of that furniture,
including the bed stand that she becomes part of, that her soul, right, becomes entrapped
within, is all cut from the native trees. Okay. Right. And so this is not just about
home furnishings. This is
about the forest. I feel like this show is like the serial iteration of that
video game mist or ribbon. You know, did you play those? Alan Wake. Well, Alan Wake
came later was influenced by Twin Peaks. So I know it's influenced by Twin Peaks, but I think
it yeah, I've never played the mist. I just know that's somewhere down the
wake. Yeah. But so that's that's the key. We're talking about whether someone can
escape the woods and escape the trees.
Okay.
Because, and you have to take in terms of her actions leading up to that, that end up
getting her condemned to that fate, involve her going into the woods in sort of a metaphorical
way.
You have to think about sort of the mythological views of the first settlers of the
Northwest, right?
I hope the woods is the place of which craft
and the place of evil.
is where deals were made with the devil.
OK, that makes a lot of sense.
All right.
OK.
And then also is Bob Merlin.
Oh, man, he wants to do a follow-up.
OK.
OK, then I'm going to have to talk about it.
All right.
So we'll talk about it.
I'm going to say I'm the man of 1,000 hair.
Excuse me, come on.
It goes without saying.
There we go.
OK.
All right.
OK, then.
I think we have, I think,
called back Hunter from the state of
perdition. You have returned to a state of
grace. Yes. Hunter, do we have you
back? Hey, yeah, I'm here. All right.
All right. Yeah. So I guess what I was
getting at was just I know as far as I
know at least I've been to a few
orthodox services and how does it
it's my understanding that in order
receive can be
as an orthodox Christian, you also need to make a good confession and do a lot of the
same things we do. So I guess what I'm wondering is, from your perspective, how is the theology
different as opposed to the Catholic way of looking at it?
The theology in general of the entire orthodox tradition versus the entire idea of a state
state of grace.
Right, yes.
Okay, yes.
All right.
.
Yeah, and so the I mean the core is not that I mean obviously yes
We do those things and you should do those things right those are good things to do
The difference I think is in the idea and the problem from our perspective is in the idea that
your
Eternal destiny is determined by whether you happen to die in a moment when you are
in that state or in a moment when you're not.
Uh-huh.
Right.
Rather than by the overall trajectory of your life.
Judging the entirety of somebody's life as a whole versus in the moment in which they
died.
Yeah.
In that moment what state was their soul in?
Right.
Okay.
That, that to me and that's sort of the context if I'm remembering right where it came
up was we were talking about the judgment and judging a whole life.
Yeah, rather than just yeah rather than just your final moment and I think
A view that it's based on the final moment runs into all kinds of problems in real pastoral situations
Right people with dementia yeah or the fact that almost everybody almost everybody that we deal with their end of life now is sedated
Yeah, like like almost no one gets to do a final confession anymore
any more. Really? So there's yeah.
And so there's a lot of pastoral issues there and stuff too.
Yeah, and so, right, like all the things that the Roman Catholic Church, well, pretty much,
right?
I mean, there are some things, little things we disagree about, but the main things
that the Roman Catholic Church says that you should do to be in and maintain a state
of grace are all things you should do.
Yes, right.
We're not disagreeing with that part, right?
more um
removing the anxiety of, right, like when you mess up as we all do, right?
Is there like this critical moment where if you don't get to confession and you get hit
by a plus, learn whatever.
Yeah.
Okay.
Yeah, that makes sense.
Yeah, I think a lot of robot Catholic
and included clergy, don't believe that that legalistically.
Right.
And I have to say, I don't either.
I mean, there was, I mean, what my life
where it gave me some anxiety
because that's how I kind of understood it,
at least on the surface.
You know, and as I've grown up,
I've kind of, I think my views become more nuanced,
but yeah, that is something that, you know,
in your brain.
up a good point about people being in end of life care. I mean, I've lost two grandparents
and I have another grandparent who he's kind of in that stage right now where I mean,
he's not actively dying, but he's got dementia and it's like that. That is something that's
kind of crossed my mind. So yeah, yeah. Thank you all for taking my call. I appreciate
Absolutely. Absolutely. Thanks for calling. Okay, we're going to take two more calls.
and then we'll have some final comments and then that'll be episode 100.
So, all right.
And we're going to keep it 100.
All right, next to last caller, welcome to Lord of Spears Podcast.
An ultimate.
Hello.
Hello. Welcome. Who are we talking to?
This is Rob from Kalamazoo, Michigan.
Rob from Kalamazoo!
I got people not relative
you? A relative of who? Are you Dutch Rob? Are you Dutch? My wife's family is. Do you
own the Heisenges? Yeah, they're running for office around here right now. Now Calamazoo
Heisenges, a lot of them are related to make. How about that? Fantastic. The other
Damicks live in that general region. Actually, the other Damicks. That's where my dad lived
is a kid.
That's right, I was born and lived as a kid.
That's why I've got a lot of Calvinists up here.
There are cousins there.
Yeah.
Yeah, Michigan weather can do that to you.
Big Dutch could do that.
That as well, yes.
I'm a weather right now.
I'm not feeling very Calvinist.
There's kind of a chicken egg issue with the weather
and being Dutch and Calvinism.
I don't know.
Rob, what's on your mind?
The Greek word stasis, I think it means to stand.
standing. Yeah.
being in hypostasis and
Eustasis
I wonder if there's anything like to be said about that if it's really just you know pass over it
It's just being used twice. I don't know. Is there anything to be taken away from that?
So
He posted a season. What was the other one that you mentioned?
Used to cease like the standing up again the resurrection. Oh, that's Anastasis
Anastasis. Yeah, yeah
Yeah.
like, Evstussees would be like standing well.
You gain good standing.
Yeah, being good standing.
Yeah, I mean, yeah, as much as I super,
I don't even have my etymology jingle ready to go here,
but I mean, such as I love like etymologizing words
and saying, see it means this,
you can't, like, epostasis,
it doesn't mean something standing.
Yeah, it kinda does though.
Okay, so tell me how it does.
Kind of does.
Okay, go ahead.
It's like literally standing.
Yeah, well, the, the Epo there is under.
Under standing under.
So what stands underneath?
Yeah, I mean, it's metaphor.
What is in what?
It's translated as substance, yeah.
Yeah.
Substance or persons underneath.
Or sub.
Substance.
Yes.
It's a calc as they call it, yes.
Yeah.
So, but it's, and this is the substance accidents, right?
distinction in Aristotle is where the term
first sort of comes to philosophical prominence is the idea that it's what stands so accidents
are like the appearance right so the substance is what stands beneath the appearance so it's
what something actually is is the idea yeah it's not it's not standing in a literal sense no
yeah no but it's standing in a metaphorical sense and it is what that's why substansia gets
like
very literally translated over.
And Anastasis also standing through a very literal,
yeah, standing back up again, right?
You've, someone who's laying down stands up again,
rises to their feet.
And uprising also.
Yes, before that's used, so with that being used
for the resurrection, there's a completely other
Greek word that's used when the New Testament talks about
about Jesus rising from the dead.
When it says Jesus rose from the dead,
it's not using a form of anostasis.
It's using a form of Aeero.
Isn't it like exedogesis?
I think.
I'm trying to remember now.
I don't know.
It's Aeero is a form of it.
It's a form of that verb.
Sometimes just Aeero, right,
his eye would be I rise, but, you know.
Aeero would be he rises.
Well that's Christ rose from the dead.
But throughout the Old Testament,
you find this a lot in the Psalms,
and the Psalms versus are used as the Prochemana
in our matten service before the Gospel reading.
The resurrection Gospel reading.
The word in Greek on SD is used, right?
And that's a imperative directed toward God,
is in a rhizogod in judge the earth.
Yep.
rise of God, lift up that hand and forget.
not the humble, right? And that's calling on God to act, right? The arise is, right? He's enthroned,
right? He's seated in the heavenly places. The any of arise is God act again, right? He took
his seat at the end of creation, calling on God to act in the judge of the earth. And so when Christ's
rising from the dead is described in the New Testament as the Anastasis, right?
that saying more than just he stood up again.
Right after being dead,
it's really referring to,
this is how God has now acted.
Right, again in history.
This is that arising that the prophets
and the Psalms were calling for
is what happens in the resurrection of Christ.
Yeah, like in a very ultimate sense.
Yeah.
Yeah, it's happened in Christ.
Yeah, yeah.
All right, well thank you very much for calling.
Thank you, fathers.
All right, we're gonna take one more caller on this,
the, the, the, the hundredth episode,
the fourth anniversary episode of the Laura Spears podcast.
Soon it will become the last episode,
but just in that sense of, on our last episode.
Yeah, we've, we already promised you like a few minutes ago,
a hundred in first episodes.
Exactly, there will be at least one more.
Yeah, that's a screaming eagle episode.
Welcome, Collar.
Hello.
So what are we talking to?
This is John from Cleveland.
John from Cleveland.
You named your city Cleveland?
I'm the last caller.
I will hopefully send this out on the lighter note.
Okay.
That father D. Young may have an interest in.
A number of years ago, the Catholic diocese in South Cleveland,
dialysis in South Cleveland.
where I live. I settled a long and raging argument and I want to see what your
opinion is and what the orthodox opinion is. Our turtle and alligator meat of fish.
Fish. Oh we've had this before. Oh you have. We have. I got a ruling on this
amount of mouth-a-thos. Yeah. Yeah there. When I moved down here because we
some gator down here. You can have them on fish days.
And yes, it's in fish. Reptiles consider fish any day you could have fish you could have.
It's good because I live kind of in real South Cleveland. Cleveland, Tennessee right now.
Father, father, young will understand. Oh, oh, you're you in Cleveland east of me?
Yes, I mean, I mean, I mean, I have a 225 area code, so yeah, okay, oh that's leave.
Yes, not not Howard the ducks Cleveland
No, no, no, I'm originally from New Orleans, but that question got that question raged on in the Catholic diocese in Baton Rouge
for years until some the bishop finally settled it with a decree
Okay, yeah, right. I mean I'm glad that they care about fasting, you know?
You know, that is the second best Louise.
the adabishops decree I've ever heard of.
Do you want to know the first?
I do now.
I'm intrigued.
I want to know the first.
So the first was the Episcopal Bishop of New Orleans.
Okay.
So there were a bunch of churches there that would basically sell booze before and after
services like Moses.
And so some people moved there and showed up at these churches and they were complaining
about all the drinking.
Right.
And so the bishop said a letter this was posted in the church and it said you know
Recently I've heard many complaints about the selling of and consumption of alcohol here at at
The church these complaints must stop
I was that is the greatest
Yeah, wow
We sort of whiskey pale whiskey paleions. I know who's gonna be the first to say that
you know the old joke about wherever you find 4p.s.d. you find a 5p.s.d.d.d.d
all right thank you father for everything happy 100th and we'll be listening to it for you
next time. all right thank you and by the way and yeah go ahead
i would say father to young if you're if you're ever on on my side of the achaph all i
talk to jules he knows who i am i'll take it lunch jules
Will you take me to Shake Shack?
No!
Oh!
I don't know that.
Ha ha ha!
We'll see about that way I go to Shake Shack or Weederstinsel.
So...
No, no, no, no. I got better places in Baton Rouge for that.
Wow.
Well, trust me.
Well, thank you all very much.
Congratulations.
Father's bless.
Happy 100th.
Thank you very much.
Yeah, before we
wrap this one up. I just want to let everybody know in case you have not heard.
Even though we don't have dates that we're going to announce just yet, nor a
location that we are going to announce just yet, although both.
No details are information.
Both have been determined.
So stop with the lobbying people.
I know it's like there's competition like.
Cities should bid.
There we go.
That's right.
They should court us like they do Taylor's.
right? Right. Just like that. Yeah. We make a major economic impact. We do. No.
Yes, there will be a Lord of Spirits conference in 2025. So I would say save the
dates, but there's no dates for me to tell you to save just yet. But they have
I'm telling you where and why and how long it will happen there.
It will happen.
The dates have been chosen.
in the location has been chosen. They're just not not
not announceable quite yet. And also, as we mentioned a couple
times earlier in the episode, next week, Father Stevens got a
new book out, Saint Paul the Pharisee. So y'all don't want
to get that. And it'll be at store.nationfaith.com. Ignore all
other outlets before you buy from from there.
There's what they're not ignoring if you look at me. I know, I
know, but we're not going to tell it. We're not going to tell
people, yeah. Get it for us.
you support publishers and authors better when you buy things directly from the publisher.
That is God's own honest truth.
So, right, so this episode has been about change in the Christian religion, change in
the religion of the worship of the one true God and what constitutes legitimate change.
And I wanted to just pick up one of the threads that we put down towards the end.
meditate on that for a minute. And that is that it's very tempting, especially
for those of us who are kind of high info Christians, which Lord of
Spirit's listener, that might be you. It's very tempting for those of us that
are high info, you know, and I'm not saying that makes us knowledgeable, just high
info like lots of info.
It's not a good thing. It's not a bad thing in and of itself.
It's tempting for us to think that Christianity consists in getting all the information correct.
You know line it all up correctly, get it all correct and
especially with Orthodox Christianity where there's so many details to
to
Look at it as like you know, which is the poison M&M in the jar?
You know you get this one thing wrong and
And it's all bad.
You kill your salvation, whatever it might be.
It's very tempting to think that way.
And especially for those of us who are high info Christians,
and particularly those who came into the Orthodox church
of our own volition a little bit later in life,
not having been raised in it, to think
that that is what consists in being an author.
like that's what it means to be orthodox.
Get all these things right.
Get all the rules right, get all the theology right,
get the dogma lined up.
I mean, I see, I mean, we've mentioned this before,
but I mean, I see endless, endless,
it seems battles on Twitter,
or I'm sorry, X, formerly known as Twitter.
That's how we have to call it now, that whole phrase.
Or on Facebook, or on social media in general,
about very, very specific philosophical questions
about Christology.
or about all kinds of stuff.
And by no means am I saying that that stuff doesn't matter.
I'm not saying it doesn't matter, but, but.
The context in which those conversations are happening
is not a context in which the outcome of those conversations
is actually being applied pastorally to people
who are trying to live their Christian lives.
It's not. It's not.
admit it, it's not. It's the context is people who want to be right, and it
does nothing wrong with wanting to understand that stuff and get it right.
There's nothing wrong with that, right? The reality is that most people,
throughout history, who have been Christians, to be traditional, to be a
traditional Orthodox Christian.
is not about lining up all the details of tradition
and getting them correct.
It's not for most of them.
And I would say for the ones who actually made it,
for sure we know and made it for sure and are saved,
that we know them so for sure that they're saved,
that we call them saints,
and we put them in our church services
and make icons of them, right, the saints.
being traditional means.
being obedient within the context of the community that God has placed you.
Right? It means doing the things on the ground that actually are hopeful to other people,
the crews of buying your own will, sacrificing your own preferences, putting other people first.
Right? If I'm not saying that to just like throw it a kind of like...
I've actually had people say this, I guess, it's just moralism by no means.
By no means at all, right?
But the point is, is that those of us who are high info, we often think that because
we have high info, then that means that we are qualified to make the determinations about
what constitute acceptable variation or unacceptable variation.
And the truth is that most of us are not qualified.
Most of us do not have the authority to do that.
and no vox popular vox dey is not a Christian doctrine. It's not just because lots of people say
something does not mean that that is the voice of God speaking. Lots of people have often said a
lot of horrible things all at the same time. There are videos of the people doing this.
The reason why we give this outline of this arc of Christian history and of what we would regard
is probably normally as pre-Christian.
in history but as we've tried to insist is actually still one religion, the worship of the
one true God throughout all of human history, is not so that we can take it in hand and say,
aha, I have the skull it's in key, we're called this out and I can apply it to other people.
It's rather actually God willing to deflate some of the inflation that exists, the tension
that exists for people to realize like
Look, actually, the point is to follow God with what it is that you've been given.
That is the point.
And to realize that it is not any of our place
to throw condemnation, frankly,
at people who are in, as we said, part of heretical bodies.
We're not saying they're not a heretical body, right?
Like I saw, for instance,
An orthodox priest talking about
a body that, you know, I would regard as having certain
heretical beliefs.
And he talked about that they were living in utter darkness,
in utter darkness, right?
I'm thinking like, well, number one,
who exactly is gonna be converted by that kind of language?
I, maybe, I don't know, maybe somebody likes to be shocked
into it or whatever, I don't know,
I'm sure they're out there.
But it's also simply not true.
not utter darkness. Things that people get right, they get right. You can't say it's all
darkness because they got this one thing wrong. It's not all darkness. Faithfulness is faithfulness.
Remember the Ninevites. Demon worshipping pagans. Who repented? God honored their repentance.
He held them up as examples against people who had all the correct info. Remember that.
than inner vides.
Everything that's good comes from God. There is nothing good that comes from some other source.
Nothing, nothing at all.
So, as we consider this big arc,
I think that it's important to bring it always back to that point of,
okay, what am I going to do with this? What has God given me to do with this?
And how can I use this
information that I have received now in a way that is actually
going to be for my salvation for the salvation of other people, like actually. Not just interesting,
fun stuff that I can get right now. But on the ground, you know, where we actually are saved,
love one another and love God above all. So, Father, what do you have to say for
what do you have to say for yourself, Father Stephen? Do you?
Well, making your way in the world today takes everything you've got.
Folks especially in, I mean, I was supposed to speak first and foremost for American society
because that's where I live.
But I think this extends beyond that.
People right now don't have an easy road in terms of figuring out life.
a lot of ways and pre-
generations, especially if you go back a few generations, things were sort of
allotted and handed to you, right? Your marriage was sort of arranged in your
career was sort of arranged and your education was sort of arranged. And you had
a, you know, from your birth or shortly thereafter you had a path set in front
of you for you to walk through the world, you know, for the rest of your life
basically. You have
a lot in life. And that is very much not true anymore for the vast majority of us. If you
think you might want to get married and have kids, you've got to figure that out. You've
got to find a person to do that with and try and find the right person who you're going
to be able to do that with over a lot of years. And how do you figure that out? And how do
you know and what I do and and you got
figure out what do I want to do for a living? What will actually pay for me to be able
to live? I haven't got to have to cobble together two, three, four things to try and just
survive, right, and live, let alone have some kind of quote-unquote career that leads
to a retirement or something. And how am I going to qualify myself? Where and how can
I get education and how much debt should I take on to do it?
and on and on and on and on and on. And for us religion, including for Christians Christianity,
has ended up getting treated very much the same way. It's one more thing you got to figure out.
Now, kind of fortunately, you may have a default setting on that still.
But if you're a person who was raised religious
You were probably brought up in some particular Christian or other religious community
and
You know you could always default to that you can sort of just keep doing that and
Take that one thing off the table
But that's not what happens that much anymore when you look at the actual landscape of things
First of all a lot of people aren't brought up within your religion so they don't have a default
But even those who are
frequently for various reasons become dissatisfied with that situation and then
either way you're out into the world trying to figure that out too. And it's very
much framed by our culture, the way our culture frames everything in this
consumeristic way where okay I mean I go I figure out what I think is right
and what I believe based on right.
books that I find convincing and
Preaching on the internet or TV or wherever that I find convincing of certain ideas and then
What's that kind of settle on what I think is probably right and what I like and what I think?
It should be like then I try to find a church that matches that and guess what there never is one
So I try to figure out like well, okay, this this place has this and that place has that
I guess I'll go to this one because you know it's got most
of the things and the things that doesn't have I can live with. And at least for now,
right? And then other things happened later and unsettled that, you know, new pastor that
changed the worship style, something else happens. This and that happens. You find out something
you didn't know before. You change your mind. And all of this is just this kind of
of chaos and do things.
anxiety, where this burden is being heaped on people as individuals, meaning separated
from their communities, their families, their, no, this is you have to figure this out
for yourself.
It's all dropped on people.
It's all dropped on people at an age when they're not prepared to do any of it.
I think some of the colors we had tonight and what we talked about tonight.
a lot to do with an antidote for that, or at least another way of approaching that.
There is a way of being in the world, there is a way of life, there is a way of worshiping
the true God that has existed for as long as humanity has existed.
Not identical, but fundamentally the same.
And there are various other ways of being in the world.
that have sort of fallen away from that over the years.
Whether they fell away from it very early on,
whether they fell away from it
in the Neolithic Revolution with it fell into paganism,
whether they fell away from it.
Had a later period into some kind of religious thing
of their own devising by artificially shoving things together,
or they fell away from it by following some heretical idea
idea that distorted that truth.
faith, that true way of being in the world, that true way of worshipping God, but
there are all these ways that have fallen away from it. And I think we need to
approach, we need to approach, if you accept that that is true, even if you don't
accept necessarily that as I or Father Andrew would say that that is preserved
in the Orthodox Church, even if you don't accept that Orthodox Church Park,
except that that is true.
then it behooves you not to try to figure all these things out for yourself.
Guess what you don't have to? It's your lucky day. This is one thing you don't have to do that with.
But rather to find the place that practices that way of life. Father Andrew,
I believe that is the Orthodox Church that has preserved that. But you know, to find it,
to find the place where they...
is and then to place yourself within it. And then this will be one thing in your life
that you don't have to be in charge of, that you don't have to struggle with, that you
don't have to yank the reins on or turn the steering wheel. This will be a place where
you can learn and you can be shaped and you can be formed and you can be transformed,
You can be healed and you can be helped.
Right.
And as that process happens, the really good news is that process and doing that process
within a community of other people who you'll be bonded with, right?
Is that same transformation and that same thing is happening with them will also help you
a whole lot with all those other things you have to figure out.
It won't do all the work for you, but it'll go a long way and it'll help an awful lot
with all those other things.
So next time we're going to kind of pick up where we sort of left off after the second
half we're going to talk about modernism and some other things.
But for now we need to work on reorienting, right?
Is religion something I figure out and then do as I think best?
Christianity is a way of being that I can come into and be shaped and formed by.
These are all passive words.
Well, I work on all these other things these other responsibilities that that life presents to me
Amen
That's our 100th episode everybody. Thanks for listening if you didn't happen to get through to a slide
Thank you for that father Steven who we'd still like to hear from you
You can also email us at Lord of Spirits at AncientFate.com.
You can message us at our Facebook.
Facebook page or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash Lord of
Spirits and if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity or in need
help to find an actual parish in the 3D world head over to OrthodoxInchro.org
Enjoy this for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the
month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific. And if you're on Facebook you can follow
our page, join our discussion group, leave ratings and reviews on all the
appropriate places and some inappropriate places if you like but most
Most importantly, share this show with a friend.
and was going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.AxerFace.com
stroke support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Thank you.
Good night.
God bless you.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father
Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
a listener-supported presentation of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld, and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne, and the beasts, and the elders,
and the number of them was ten thousand times ten thousand, and thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power, and riches, and wisdom, and strength, and honor, and glory, and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11
Here is Mother Gabrielle.